🎵
🎵
The Fall Education takes two
The Fall Education tark två
As the19 month is over
As the19 month is over
impress many welcome each other
impress many welcome each other
Kings
Kings
Playing
Playing
down
down
civil
民
movie
movie
then
then
It means that you all have a speech in your hands.
就是你們手上都有一個演講在要
Of course you can take a look first
當然你可以先稍微看一下
and after listening to the speech
然後聽完演講以後
you go back and read it again
你再回去再念一次
Then there will be a deeper experience
然後會有更深的體會
You only need to understand when you go back
你只要回去以後念得懂的
understandable words
念得通的話
That's very rewarding
那就是很有收穫了
content of that speech
那對演講的內容
I will be introduced by teacher Wang Yuling
我就由王毓玲老師來跟你們介紹
at the beginning
在開場的時候
I still put his simple travel law
我還是把他的這個簡單的旅律
with his glorious deeds
跟他的光榮事蹟
Give you a brief introduction
跟大家做簡單的介紹
Dr. Wang Yuling came to the Department of Physics in 1979 and graduated
王毓玲博士是1979年來到物理系畢業
Then after graduation
然後復完畢業以後
to the University of Chicago in 1988
到芝加哥大學在1988年
PhD in Physics
拿到的物理博士
Then go to the famous Vel Lab in the United States
然後到美國有名的Vel Lab
to do postdoctoral research
去做博士後研究
Come back and join us in 1991
1991年回來加入我們的
Original branch Re-researcher To researcher To current specific researcher
原分所 復研究員 到研究員 到現在的特定研究員
He has performed very well all the way
他一路都是表現得非常的優異
In terms of research he has two main themes
在研究方面 他有主要的兩個課題
The first topic is the surface of the rice
第一個課題是這個表面的這個耐米的
The mechanism underlying the formation of this surface structure
這個表面的結構的形成的基礎的機制
In this regard, he said that in the particle of Naimi
在這方面 他就說在耐米的這個粒子裡頭
has its specific shape and number
有他的特定的形狀跟數目
Call this Magic Class
叫做這個Magic Class
This is a very strange group of people
就是特別奇異的這個人組
This is the basic research
這個是基本基礎的這個研究
It has also received a lot of affirmation
在這方面也受到很多的肯定
For example, this domestic outstanding talent talks about doing
比如說這個國內的傑出人才講做
Youyang Technology
有洋科技技
I want to do a meeting of the Chinese American Physical Society
想做中華美國物理學會的會事
American Physical Society Meetings, etc.
美國物理學會的會事等等
What about the second research direction?
另外第二個研究方向呢
Is the material resistant to this result of imitation
是耐擬的這個結果的材料
Especially in this Yangji Yanghua
尤其在這個楊吉養化的這個
Anti-fear materials in Yang Ji's Yanghua
楊吉的這個養化里的耐擬恐動材料
Then this and this and these two
那這個都跟這個這兩個
The second one is related to what I'm going to talk about today.
第二個都跟這個今天要講的有關係
After glutinous rice is afraid of moving materials
糯米恐動材料以後
can turn some metals into some
就可以再把一些金屬變成一些
That neat arrangement
那個俱正的這個排列
Then use this to do the next step with this and use
然後用這個去做下一步的這個併用
That part of the research results
那一部分的研究成果
Also received a number of awards
也獲得多項的獎項的肯定
Like the Executive Yuan Science and Technology Contribution Award
像行政院科技貢獻獎
The Ministry of Economic Affairs' Difficult Technology Industry Gold and Silver Awards, etc.
經濟部的難以科技產業金銀獎等等
In addition to his research
那他除了研究的
Also contribute to academic administration, which is what we call service academic sociology
在學術行政也就是我們講的服務學術社學方面也有貢獻
He used to be a senior member of the National Science Department of Physics
他曾經兼任國科物理學門的高級人
There are also two directors of the hospital who broke up with the hospital, etc.
還有本院的兩任本院分手的所長等等
The topic he talked about today is very interesting
今天他講的題目非常有意思
Help us listen to the sound from bacteria with Laimi Optical Art
用賴米光學科藝幫我們聽來自細菌的聲音
Our warm applause welcomes Laimi Optical Science
我們熱烈的掌聲歡迎賴米光學科
Thank you, President Peng, for the invitation
謝謝彭學院長的邀請
Thank you very much for the long introduction
也非常感謝大家做了這麼長的介紹
I speak on many occasions
我去很多場合演講
No one has ever told so much about my not-so-honorable past
從來沒有人把我過去不是那麼光榮的經歷講得這麼仔細
Before I came here today, I was actually very, very cautious
我今天來之前其實我是非常非常謹慎的
Because I probably told you that if you want to give such a speech, you must be legendary.
因為我大概跟你們講說你要去做這樣的演講一定要傳奇裝
tie
打領帶
so my tie is here and my suit is here
所以我的領帶是有帶在這裡的西裝也在這裡
everyone to see the proof
大家去看到證明
After a few minutes, it still looks like this
幾個分鐘後還有穿過這樣子
Then when I came in, I saw the curator Angel wearing this
那我一進來看到天使館長穿這樣
I'll just take him off and leave him here like this
我就趕快把他脫掉然後就丟在這裡這樣子
I'm really, really honored today
那今天我真的非常非常榮幸
I have such an opportunity to talk to you
有這樣一個機會來跟大家
Borrowing this night, everyone should be watching that
借用這個晚上大家那個本來是應該在看
Is it time to turn around or something?
真團轉還是什麼之類的時間呢
come here everyone
來這邊大家
Let's talk about some science
跟大家聊一聊一些科學
interesting things above
上面有趣的事情
That just left the stage and mentioned to me
那剛退場跟我提到說
This time should be reserved a little more for the following questions, which should be more exciting
這個時間應該多留一點點給後面的問題應該是比較精彩
so i'm going to talk
所以我準備講
20 minutes to fix it
20分鐘就把它解決了
That
那
because I saw
因為有看到
Because there are some colleagues in there who are experts
因為裡面有一些同仁他們是專家
Because I'm actually a person who doesn't understand biology at all.
因為我其實是一個完全不懂生物的人
Then I suddenly talk about video here
那我突然在這邊講視訊
It's actually something that scares me a little.
其實是一個讓我有一點膽戰心驚的事情
But like these two pictures
不過就像這張這兩張圖
What I see here are bacteria, red snowballs, and rice-resistant liquid.
我這邊看到的上面的這邊就是細菌、紅雪球、耐米液質
I will introduce you step by step
我會一步一步的跟大家介紹
I hope that the youngest kid who is doing this can understand what I say
我希望在做那位最年輕的小朋友都能夠聽得懂我講什麼
Then I'll go ahead and talk about it
那我就先進入往下講
but good
可是好
Before I talk about it, I want to introduce what is the original branch cable
要講之前我要先介紹一下什麼是原分索
Because I am in this original branch
因為我在這個原分索
Everyone has heard it, but they don't know what the original branch cable is
大家都聽到了,都不知道原分索是什麼
This word will really disappear
這個字真的會不見
There is still a level above
上面還是有一階的
its first half is also missing
它的上半節也是不見的
this place
這個地方
The reason lies in
原分索在
National Taiwan University campus
台大的校內
It is not the original separate cable
它不是原來就分開的索
This is very important, because once there was an English translation and then it came back and translated the original content for us.
這點非常重要,因為真的有一次有一個英文的翻譯然後就翻回來就幫我們翻譯原分索
That is to say, it is the history of the original division, which is the original division.
那就是說就是解原分索的歷史,它是原來分開的索
I want to explain to you first
我要跟大家先解釋一下
Yuan Tianchun is in the Zhengdong room of the National Taiwan University campus
袁天璿是在台大校園的正東間
Later that year
待會去當年就是
Dean Peng's Department of Chemistry at National Taiwan University
彭院長的台大化學系
Take down the old building
把舊化館拆下來
let's settle there
讓我們在那邊定居
Because Dr. Yuan Ze
因為袁澤博士
When Academician Yuan Ze was teaching at Bote University
袁澤院士當年在博特大學教書的時候
He came back to promote in Taiwan
他就回來在台灣推動
Hope to establish the research of atomic and molecular science
希望成立原子與分子科學的研究
Atoms and molecules are not originally separated
原子與分子不是原來就分開
in this way
這樣子
The study of atoms and molecules
原子與分子這個研究
Why set up in Central Research
為什麼要在中央研究裡面成立
actually you talk about it
其實你把它講
Atoms are talking about physics
原子講的是在講物理
Molecules talk about chemistry
分子講的是在講化學
So the original branch is actually
所以原分所其實就是
Institute of Physical Chemistry in Central Research Institute
中央研究裡面的物理化學所
That is, we have two
也就是我們有兩個
big brother or big sister
大哥或是大家姐
sandwiched here
夾在這邊
we're going in the canyon
我們要在峽崩裡面
the whole survival place
全生存那個所
was sent to National Taiwan University
就被外放到台大
So it looks like it was originally separated.
所以看起來也是原來就分開來的所
The first point is inside the campus of National Taiwan University
第一點是在台大校園裡面
It is on the small and medium East Road in their Taiwan University campus
就是他們講台大校園裡面的中小東路上面
National Taiwan University Tourism Bureau
台大遊局這邊
If you go to the National Taiwan University campus
如果你到台大校園裡面
We have a National Taiwan University campus that has become very beautiful now
我們有一個台大校園現在已經變得非常漂亮
It's worth seeing
很值得大家去看
has a nice seat
有一個很漂亮的座椅
In fact, there are many scenery at night
晚上其實有很多風景
It's all worth sharing with you
都是很值得跟大家分享
Then you'll see a landmark over there
那你就看到那邊有個地標
There is a sculpture beside the game board
遊局邊上有一個雕塑
The name of this sculpture is Dot
這雕塑名字叫做點
a chance to wait if someone asks me
有機會等一下如果有人問我
I'm explaining to you what I call a point
我在跟你解釋我什麼叫做一個點
it's me
這是一個我個人
A sculpture I raised for fundraising when I was in office
我在所長任內的時候去募款募來的一個雕塑
I think it is the most beautiful sculpture on the campus of National Taiwan University
我認為是台大校園裡面最漂亮的雕塑
is my biggest
是我最大的
The greatest contribution to this artifact
對於這個文物最大的貢獻
so i have to tell
所以我一定要講一下
This matter welcomes the young friends here to go there to talk about love
這件事情歡迎在座的年輕的朋友到那邊去談戀愛
Then go there to take wedding photos
然後以後到那邊去照婚紗照
This is my artistic wish
這個是我文藝的願望
Then my current director is Professor Zhou Meiying
那我現在的所長是周美穎教授
see you next time
我們下次再見
In fact, a very stable theoretical physicist
其實一個非常穩定的理論物理學家
he was originally in america
他本來是在美國的
Chair of Georgia Tech's Department of Physics
Georgia Tech的物理系當系主任
After the end of the five-year tenure of the department chair
系主任五年任內結束之後
He'll come back and pick me up
他就回來接我的位置
Become Academia Sinica
成為中央研究院
number one since the original
原始以來第一位
Director of your tree pear group
你的樹梨組的所長
is a founder
就是一個創立者
just tell you
就告訴你們說
Heritage water has one great benefit
文物水有一個非常好處
Heritage Water Does Not Discriminate
文物水沒有性別歧視
is also very important
也是非常重要的一點
Our director is also this year
我們所長也在這一今年
very important one
非常重要的一個講
She is an outstanding female scientist in Taiwan
就是台灣的女傑出科學家
Then this year's Taiwan female outstanding scientist
那到今年的台灣女傑出科學家
so i stop here
所以我講到這裡
That is, when the advertising time of the original committee is over
就是當原始委的廣告時間講完了
Aim does not want to be in this young friend
目的不希望在這個年輕的朋友
I have the opportunity to go to the original commission to fall in love
有機會到原始委去談戀愛
in this way
這樣子
good
好
Then what I'm going to talk about today
那我今天要講的題目
Just now the vice president has read
剛剛副院長已經念過
I won't talk about it in particular
我就不會特別再去講
I hope to take this opportunity to convey a lot to you
希望在藉這個機會跟大家傳達很多
In fact, it is very unfamiliar to the general public.
其實對於一般社會大眾都是很陌生的
For example, when I heard Lai Nv
比方說聽到賴女
Some people say that Lai Nv still has sex with Charity Girl
有人說賴女還跟慈善女
Or it's not the same in the female tour group or something like that
或在來女遊族不一樣 諸如此類
that optical technology
那光學科技
then listen to the sound of bacteria
然後聽細菌的聲音
My original version had no parentheses
我本來的版本是沒有括號的
Then I thought it was dangerous
後來想 我這很危險
Because there are experts out there
因為底下還有專家
Wait a minute to get out by my co-workers
等一下出去被我的物理化學同事
Fix it again and say you are cheating on this and that
修理一遍說你這個那個欺騙
It's not right to ride a cheater
騎騙俠 這樣也不對
So I just bracket it like this
所以我就只要把它括號起來這樣子
That's a laser light over here.
那這邊照的是一個雷射光
and then after passing through a bacterium
然後穿過一個細菌之後
Then this bacterium is
然後這個細菌是
The fungus shells are attached to a Lai's silver array
菌殼就貼在一個賴女的銀的陣列上面
Then you this is an aperture laser light
然後你這個是一個光圈雷射光
After photographing and passing through
照下來穿過之後
And then that laser light comes in
然後那個雷射光進來
is a green light
是一個綠色的光
go out and become a
出去變成一個
Turn into a shade, turn into yellow light and go out
變成一個屏蔭 變成黃色的光出去
Then we go to detect that light change
然後我們就去偵測那個光的變化
then i can tell you
然後我可以告訴你說
In fact, who is this matter with?
其實這件事情跟誰
the sound is very close
聲音是很接近的
We rely on measurements like this
我們就靠這樣的測量
Another picture is
另外這個圖是
Similarly this array above
同樣這個陣列上面
I
我
After laying a layer of eons of people
鋪了一層萬古人數之後呢
above this array
這個陣列上面就
become easier to catch bacteria
變得很容易把細菌抓住
we catch germs
我們就把細菌抓住
that blood cell ignores it
那血球不理它
Then catch the bacteria from the blood
那就從血液裡面去抓細菌
come to listen
來聽
sound from bacteria
來自於細菌的聲音
if everyone knew
如果大家都知道
like you listen to an instrument
就像你聽樂器一樣
If you can hear the quality of that instrument
如果你聽得到那個樂器的音質的話
you can probably guess
你大概可以猜出
Four or Five Cello or Violin
四五大提琴還是小提琴
the same you can probably guess
那同樣的你可能可以猜出來
what bacteria
是什麼細菌
what about these voices
那這件事情對這些聲音
yes there is some help
是有一些幫助的
so this is what i've said
所以這就是我已經講完了
so let's start asking questions now
那我們現在就開始問問題了
Can
可以
OK
OK
then i think
那我想
it's more purposeful than
這比有點目的
Let's talk about Laimi first, okay?
先講賴米好不好
Let's explain Raimi
我們解釋一下賴米
we are all used to
我們大家習慣
everyone is used to
大家習慣
what everyone saw
大家看到的
probably all
大概都是
It's a tendency, that is, a meter creature
這是一個傾向,就是一公尺的生物
This little friend is a daughter, she looked like this when she was a child
這隻小朋友是女兒,小時候這樣子
his sister is chasing him
他姊姊正在追他
His height is one meter
他的高度就是一公尺
I call everyone Yimi
我給大家叫做一米
We are one-meter creatures, our world is one-meter creatures
我們是一米的生物,我們世界都是一米的生物
Then inserting three orders of magnitude at once is an ant
那一下子插三個數量級就是螞蟻
about a micron of a mimi
大概一個咪咪咪的一個微米
Insert another number, your one million times is the protagonist
再插一個數量,你一百萬倍的就是主角
Feelings from Dachang
大廠感鈞
When inserting another order of magnitude
再插一個數量級下去的時候
Another three orders of magnitude, when you go down a thousand times
再三個數量級,你一千倍下去的時候
From this point to this side is Ichina you
從這一點到這邊就是一奈你
There are only four atoms in total
這裡面總共只有四個原子
This is in my lab, 1998
這個就是在我實驗室,1998年
is a photo of a strange atomic cluster seen for the first time
是一張第一次看到的奇異原子團的照片
This resolution photo means
這張分辨照就是說
This work is my first doctoral student
這個作品是我的第一個博士生
he does the best
他做出來最好
quickly gained a lot of recognition in the world
很快地在世界上得到很多的認可
We are still doing a lot of research on that aspect
我們現在還在做很多的那一方面的研究
In fact, there is no holiday in our field
其實我們這個領域並沒有放假
But that's where both of us are interested
但是那邊是我們兩個的興趣
wait a minute i'm going to talk about the tools we grind
等一下我要講的是我們磨生的工具
We are actually interested in making atoms or molecules
我們興趣其實在做原子或分子
But because I want to compete with the biotech people for a bite to eat
但是因為我要跟做生物科技人搶一口飯吃
I had to study bacteria
我只好去研究細菌
It's actually a pretty sad story
其實這是一個蠻悲情的故事
Then let me explain the meaning of scale first.
那我先把尺度這個意義好好地解釋一下
Because every time I tell you this 1000 times
因為每次跟你講這1000倍
Most of that you don't actually feel
那大部分你其實都沒有感覺
And 1000 times you don't actually feel it
而且1000倍你其實沒有感覺
But today I want to talk very practical
可是我今天要講很實際的
As long as you know what is 1000 times
你只要你知道什麼叫1000倍
Let's talk about 100 times first
我們先講100倍好了
Where was my little girl last night?
我昨天晚上這個小女生呢
She has become the tallest girl in the family
已經變成是全家最高的女生了
She is 160 cm tall
她身高160公分
Then she yelled in the room
然後她在房間裡面大叫一聲
see her as a cockroach
把她看到蟑螂
You must help me kill this cockroach
一定要幫我把這蟑螂打死
Then my heart skipped a beat, why should I help you kill the cockroaches?
那我心跳想為什麼我要幫你把蟑螂打死
Do you know the relationship between your height and the ratio of cockroaches
你知道你的身高跟蟑螂的比例的關係
if you were a cockroach
假如你是蟑螂的話
If you are a cockroach
那你是蟑螂的話
what about this person
那這個人呢
Humans are 1-0 tall
人呢 身高就是1-0這樣子
Then you'll see that one day you're yelling over there
那你會看到就有一天你在那邊大叫
Just look at 101 and move him, and then 101 keeps yelling
就是對著101 動他一眼就101就一直大叫說
Hurry up and hit him, hit him?
趕快來打他 打他嗎
Just a bunch of 101s running around on the street
就一大堆的101在街上跑來跑去
Let's say there are cockroaches, there are cockroaches, there are people
就說有蟑螂 有蟑螂 有人
of course not
當然不是這樣子
but that's weird
可是這就很奇怪
people are so strange
人就是這麼奇怪
you only see cockroaches
你只看到蟑螂
My wife stopped fighting when she saw the ants
我太太看到螞蟻的時候就已經紛爭不堆了
That's 1000 times
那是1000倍的
1000 times means that
1000倍的意思是說
You go to Seven Star Mountain
你往七星山走過去
Your Qixing Mountain suddenly retreated 30 kilometers away
你的七星山突然倒退30公里之外去
After taking the potion, I still screamed at you
下了藥水還不天搶地的對你叫
Of course this is
那這個當然就是
It means that people actually have all the power behind you.
就是人其實對你這整個背力
that size feeling
那個大小的感覺
Let me tell you what you feel about numbers
我跟你講就數字你那個感覺
really want to think about you
跟你真正要去想
Twice already big giant
兩倍已經是很大的巨人
Like when you're twice your height walking in
比如說你身高的兩倍走進來的時候
is very scary
是非常可怕的
not to mention
更不用講
so you are seen what kushra those geography
所以你被看到什麼庫斯拉那些地理
Those Kushras have no sense
那些庫斯拉都沒有什麼差識
But one word is a thousand times
可是一講就是千倍
The most exaggerated would be to say
那最誇張的應該是說
object
對象
is the earth
就是地球
we are creatures on earth
我們是在地球上的生物
We are a million times smaller than Earth
我們跟地球尺寸大小差一百萬倍
That is to say, if you are lucky
也就是說你如果運氣不錯
you just find a good zoom spot
你就隨便找一個很好的放大景點
As soon as you look, you happen to see a certain snail beach
你一看上去就剛好看到某一個螺體海灘
It's nice to see some creatures that look like these things
就很看到有些生物很像這些東西
just lay there like this
就躺在那裡這樣子
you put this at a certain point
你把這個某一個點
One point of flashlight disaster
手電災一個點
Then when magnified a million times
然後放大一百萬倍的時候
you see these things
你就看到這些東西
actually looks about the same
其實看起來差不多
no difference
沒有什麼差別
That's a million times faster
那這是一百萬倍高速的事情
In other words, our relationship with the earth
也就是說我們跟地球的關係
The relationship between bacteria and us
跟細菌跟我們的關係
In fact, this size is just your name
其實這個大小只是你的名
same thing
同樣的這回事
so now
那所以現在
There is a noun called human ball
有一個名詞叫做人球
an earth, yes
一個地球嘛,對
so you are human ball
所以你就是人球
You and I are human balls
你跟我都是人球
finally that translation is very interesting
終於那個翻譯非常有趣
if flipping the ball
如果翻人球的話
people will laugh
一定會被人家笑的
But as long as there is a way to scrape it up
但是只要有辦法刮一刮起來
Then of course we have a lot of drama
那我們身上當然有很多戲劇
so let's see
所以我們就看一下
drama is actually a
戲劇其實是一個
There are many creatures older than us
比我們還要古老的生物很多
Because this drama has a protagonist
因為這個戲劇是有一個主先啦
In this case, I think people in the body should not dare to say such things to me.
這樣的話我覺得對身體人應該不會太敢對我這樣說
Because the earth was formed forty-five years ago
因為四十五年前的地球形成了
about thirty or forty years ago
大概在三十四十年前的時候
It turns out that the drama has already happened
原來戲劇就已經生了
There must have been ancient dramas in those days
那時候生肯定有古劇類
There's a drama up here in the whole life
整個生命處上面這邊就有個戲劇
What we now see more often
那我們現在比較常看到的
Everyone has Gram and Young's bacteria
大家身上都有格蘭氏、楊氏菌
Variety of Grammy plays
各式格蘭劇劇
Then with this time it has been
那隨著這個時間就一直
Then we are actually descendants of animals and plants
那我們其實是動植物的後代
Then our animals and plants lived about five to one billion years ago
那麼我們動植物大概在五到十億年前的
that's not very attractive
那不是非常愈聘的
Humans are very skimpy
人類是非常一撇
you only have four to eight million people
你只有四到八百萬人
It is the prime quotient of the whole life
就是整個這個生命的素商
Many of us are juniors like this
我們是非常多當後輩這樣子
so amazing
所以很奇妙
This junior is super arrogant
這後輩超級自大
I feel like everything is centered on me
就覺得一切都是以我為中心
then you will look carefully
然後你會仔細去看
I just told you about the human rights
我剛剛跟你講那個人權上面
doing things
在做的事情
will we die
我們自己會不會死掉
is that we will not treat our bacteria
就是我們會不會對我們的細菌
kill us as soon as we hear germs
把我們殺得一聽到細菌
everyone is angry
大家都很生氣
I mean, bacteria are so dirty.
就說細菌好髒啊
You see he just went to wash his hands
你看他剛去洗手
The result is a sterilizer.
結果就有一個滅菌滅啊
why is it like this everywhere
為什麼之類的到處這樣
but you will see
可是你會看說
this guy these guys
這個人這些傢伙
motion against earth
正在對地球動的動作
In fact, with bacteria trying to kill this guy
其實跟細菌想要把這個人幹掉
This thing seems to be similar
這件事情好像滿類似的
We're digging everywhere
我們到處挖礦啦
do it here
這邊弄啊
It's you who made the atmosphere dirty
就是你把大氣弄得很髒
and then why
然後為什麼之類的
Actually quite similar
其實滿類似的
there's a lot worth it
這裡面有很多值得
Let's all go and think about it
我們大家去好好去想一想說
why are we doing this
我們為什麼在做這件事情
Well that bacteria
那那個細菌弄好
kill that tree owner
就把那個樹主弄死了
but we didn't get it right it was us
但我們沒弄好是我們
maybe it's possible to kill the earth
也許有可能把地球弄死了
it's also possible
也有這個可能
So we should think about it
所以我們應該好好地去想一下
how should i do this
應該怎麼去做這件事
I highly recommend here
我在這裡強烈推薦
this book is
這個書是
Let me tell you about the one written by Lida Vice Church
講一下覺得行李達副教堂寫的一個
very popular book
非常通俗的書
everyone go back
大家回去
don't read my profile
不要看我的簡介
Just go back and buy a copy of The World of Bacteria
就回去買一本細菌的世界來看
there are very very interesting
裡面有非常非常有趣的
just don't say he has a lot of numbers
就是不要說他有很多的數字
Then he asked what he wrote in the preface
那他問他在序文裡寫的
because of his order to write such a book
因為他寫這種書的命令
It is the justice of hoping to return the bacteria
是希望還細菌的公道
so don't hear it again
所以不要再聽到
I hope you after that speech
希望你聽完那演講之後
Stop having so many prejudices about bacteria
不要再細菌有這麼多的成見
don't have that inappropriate
不要有那個不恰當的
racial contrarian
種族逆勢
I think you are much more advanced than him
就覺得你比他高級很多
Then the number of bacteria on our body
然後我們身上的細菌的數字
You can estimate it probably
你去估一下大概就在
100 megabytes that many in this episode
100兆這一集的那麼多數
In fact his numbers
事實上他的數字來講
10 times more bacteria than our body
比我們身體的細菌還多的10倍
That is to say, if we decide to make an agreement with Confidence, we will play the game of democracy.
也就是說如果假設我們跟信心大家決定說好我們就來玩民主的遊戲
we vote we only lose
我們投票我們只投輸了
because he's already 10 times bigger
因為他已經多10倍了
we are a minority
我們是少數族群
we should immediately
我們應該一下子就
Our cells vote and lose
我們的細胞就投票就結束就輸掉了
it's an interesting number
這是一個有趣的數字
There are about 1,000 kinds of beliefs in the human digestive system.
那關於是人的消化系統裡面就有大概1000種的信心
I was there
我在那裡
Most of those numbers are mostly unknown to us.
那多數字我們都絕大都是我們都不認識
none of us can cultivate
我們都沒有辦法培養
we don't know each other
我們都不認識
They're like saying a lot of life on Earth is in the wild
他們就像說地球上很多的生物都在野外
they all had a great time
他們都說過得非常愉快
But he's fine if he doesn't go to Utah
但如果不去猶他他都沒事
You don't have to put him in the zoo to raise it, it will be very difficult
你不一定要把他放到動物園裡面來養的話就很困難
There are not many animals that we can raise
我們能夠養的動物其實不多是少數
the same bacteria on our body
同樣我們身上的細菌
This is what many of my bio colleagues have said
這些在近很多我的生物的同仁說的
would agree with me
都會同意我的說法
the vast majority of these thousand species of bacteria
就是絕大多數這一千種的細菌
In fact, we have no way to train him in the experiment
我們事實上都沒有辦法去培養他在實驗
so we don't know him
所以我們都不認識他
That means
那就是說
It is more interesting to put mountain towels in the wild
放在野外的放山巾才是比較有趣的
Raising a lot of broilers for you is actually what we will raise
養一大堆給你的肉雞其實是我們會養
But it's actually less interesting
但是其實比較沒趣
Also he mentioned some very interesting things
另外他也提到一些非常有趣的事情
And then bacteria actually have a love-hate relationship
然後細菌其實有愛恨情仇
They will also have liangjingxiang
他們也會有兩菁香
Because there is an act similar to marriage
因為有類似結婚的行為
Then they also have collective wear
然後他們也有集體磨傷
Then there are also sacrifices to clamp me these actions
然後也有犧牲夾我這些動作
In fact, after reading this book, I thought
其實我看完這個書就覺得說
Professor Xu is really very, very
這個許教授真的是非常非常
very very storytelling
非常非常講故事的
write a quick
寫一個這麼快速的
I read in his preface that he seems to have finished the book in two months
我看他的序上說他好像只花兩個月就寫完這本書
I really admire him very much
我真的是非常非常佩服他
So it is highly recommended here
所以在這裡強烈的推薦
you can leave now
你可以現在就可以離開
Just read a book
你就去看本書就好了
why listen to me
幹嘛聽我講的
good
好
In addition, what I would recommend is to say
另外我要推薦的就是說
You can read last July's issue of Science Journal
你可以看去年七月期的科學會刊
Then there are two articles
那這裡面有兩篇文章
Then these two articles
那這兩篇文章
I would recommend here is to say
我會在這裡推薦就是說
one of these
這個當中有一篇
That is to say, this is shared with the continuation
就是講這與續盡共享的
Your kind of numbers are worth tasting
你那種數字是讓人值得萬味的
is why we know that there are about a thousand species of bacteria
就是我們為什麼知道大概有一千種細菌
In fact, it is because we are talking about how many genes there are in bacteria
其實是因為我們去針對菌菌說有多少基因
Not the number of genes that make our bodies like ours
不是我們身體像我們人類的基因的數字
About 20,000 to 25,000
大概兩萬到兩萬五千的
But our bacteria have 150 times more genes than us
可是我們身上的細菌的基因數字是比我們多150倍
That's the bacteria if we count it all as one organism
就是那些細菌如果我們把它全部算成一個生物的話
Let it adjust the whole kind
讓它整個調量這整個種類
In total they give us a
它們總共給我們一個
That is, if the number of genes is reversed
就是如果讓基因數來頭掉
We lost even more, right?
我們是輸得更慘對不對
We just said ten and we lost
剛剛說十個我們就輸了
And to use the numbers of genes
而且要利用基因的數字來頭
Then we lost very miserably.
那我們是跟著輸得非常光慘
There's a very biological
在這裡面有一個非常跟生物
related to medicine
跟醫學有關系的
In this article, there are also 1.0 in the Science generation.
這邊文章裡面有裡面到Science代也有1.0的這個
Professor Tetger Kasmarion is mentioned here at the very beginning of his article
特特格教授卡斯馬里恩他的文章的劈頭就有提到這裡
He said that our ability in genes
他說基因當中我們的能力
It is the point of view that the system function is better
是系統功能較佳這個觀點
interested in living on us
有興趣活在我們身上
Let our immune system function better
讓我們免疫系統功能會比較好
Such a statement is the only view on traditional
這樣一種說法是唯一對傳統的觀點
Because when we hear bacteria we think
因為我們聽到細菌就認為說
Bacteria are bad things
細菌就是壞東西嘛
It is best not to have bacteria in our seven bodies
我們七身當最好不要有細菌
But now gradually the information
可是現在漸漸的資料
Gradually more and more clear trend
漸漸的越來越明確的趨勢
is immunity
就是免疫
Missed a few words from this today
今天把這個少了幾個字
is the driver of immune system function
就是免疫系統功能的驅動力
is a symbiotic relationship
是一種共生的關係
i think you grow up
我覺得你的長大
without those bacteria
如果沒有那些細菌
Actually there are many things
其實有很多事情
your life won't be very pleasant
你的生命並不會非常愉快
If there were no bacteria on earth
地球上如果沒有細菌的話
there are too many things
有太多的事情
Including whether you drink alcohol
包括有沒有酒喝啊
or any of these things
或什麼這些事情都
There are no bacteria, everyone can't do it
都沒有細菌大家都不能做
too much fermentation
太多的發酵
These things are done by bacteria
這些事情都靠細菌在做
In fact, bacteria are one of the best
其實細菌是一個最好的
Laimi made by myself
自己組合出來的賴米
Raimi's robot
賴米的機器人
Then he will repeat himself
然後他就會自己會重複
and then do something for you
然後就會幫你做一些事
So take these loose
所以要好好散帶這些
The Laimi machine that lives with you
跟你共生的那個賴米機器
is bacteria
是細菌
this is bacteria
這是細菌
Then if those who are dependent on our civilization
那如果跟我們相依文明的那些
you look carefully
你仔細的去看
There are various types of bacteria in our gut
我們腸道裡面有各式各樣的菌
then on our skin
然後我們的皮膚上面
every place
就是每一個地方
In fact, when we come out of the mother's birth canal
其實當我們從媽媽的產道出來的
from that moment
那一刻開始
We start with a bunch of bacterial denominators
我們就開始帶著一堆的細菌分母
Then he'll be on you when he's certified
然後進證的他就會在你身上
repeated to many children
就重複到很多的小孩子
Maybe now there might be some evidence telling you that
也許現在可能有一些證據在告訴你說
If you're not well inside your bowels
如果你沒有好好的在你的腸子裡面
There is a time when a bacterial phase is wrong
有一個菌相是不對的時候
or whatever you are getting older
或是隨便你年紀越來越大
your bacteria
你的菌相
Then there is a vision in the body
然後身體裡面有一個臨像
Then there is a bacterial phase in the gut
那這個腸道裡面有一個菌相
Because the bacterial phase is when the beginning is wrong
因為菌相是開始不對的時候
your life will be out of balance
你的生活就會失去平衡
Then this moving relationship will be messed up
那這個動身關係會亂對
You won't be happier when you break
打破的時候,你並不會比較幸福
So the best way is to
所以最好的方法就是
You have to find a way to talk to your fellow bacteria
你要想辦法跟你的細菌的同胞們
Get along well and live in peace with everyone, and have a better life
好好的共處大家相安無事過得比較愉快一點
I think I should agree with Xu Minda's textbook after I explained it like this
我想我這樣講完許民達教材應該是同意的
He wants us to pay back a bacterium
他希望我們還一個細菌的功勞
Another article talks about so-called probiotics
另外一篇文章就在講所謂益生菌
I was supposed to bring a bottle or two with me today
今天本來我帶著想要帶一瓶一二瓶來
Let me tell you that when I drink one or two bottles in one gulp
就告訴你一說我這一瓶一二瓶在一口喝下去的時候
I will take the population of the whole earth by a dozen
我就把全地球的人口十幾
It was the confidence of dozens of people who drank it all in one gulp
是被幾十一的信心就一口全部喝下去了
Is that so?
這樣有沒有
Listen and see if there is a bottle or two
你聽聽看如果有一瓶一二瓶
Then his size is as big as the earth came over
然後他的大小是像地球那麼大走過來
Then drink all the people on our earth in one gulp
然後把我們地球的人就這樣一口全部喝下去
It's actually quite scary for bacteria.
對細菌們來講其實蠻恐怖的
right don't you think
對不對你不覺得嗎
Only sixty-one people disappeared.
就六十一人一口就不見了這樣
ok then we're going to start talking
好那我們就要開始來談說
what is the sound of bacteria
細菌的聲音是什麼
I'm really not satisfied with this word
這個字我實在是有點不太滿意
What is the difference between the sounds played by Ma Youyou and bacteria?
就是馬悠遊和細菌玩出來的聲音差別在哪裡
we know
我們知道的
What is Ma You playing?
馬悠遊玩的是什麼?
Everyone knows that Ma Youyou plays with a big body
大家就知道馬悠遊玩的是一個大體型
This photo is really Ma Youyou
這張照片真的是馬悠遊
Yes, but could it really be Ma Youyou?
對,但會不會真的是馬悠遊
OK
OK
This is an ad for Ma Youyou's concert
這個是一個馬悠遊的演唱會的廣告
That
那
The biggest difference between Ma Youyou and bacteria
馬悠遊跟細菌最大的差別
It's about talking about the plan
就是關於講的計畫
just a million times worse
就差了一百萬倍
Let's talk about sound
那我們開始來講聲音
so i'm going to tell you
所以我要跟你講說
its difference is
它的差別是
Where is the most important place
在最主要在什麼地方
Then it's a tone
然後這就是一個聲指
shake this thing over there
在那邊震盪這件事情
Then this shock and Ma Youyou's love sound pull the shock
那這個震盪跟馬悠遊的情音拉那個震盪
It's actually very similar
其實是很像類似的
It's just that we can't hear the vibration
只是這個震盪我們聽不到
But the voice of Ma Youyou
但是馬悠遊拉的聲音
listen 'cause i can't hear
你聽,因為我聽不到
Now of course I can ask one
那現在我當然可以問一個
One is Ma Youyou's bacteria
有一個就是馬悠遊的細菌
Natara's big body
那他拉的大體型
should
應該
where to put it frequently
頻密放在哪裡
Just for the kids over there
就是給那邊的小朋友
kid over there
那邊的小朋友
I will ask today's exam questions
我會問的今天的考題
They didn't pass the flying mention
人家沒有考通過飛提的
don't go home like this
就不准回家這樣子
This bacterium Ma Yoyo reminds everyone
這個細菌馬悠悠帶給大家提醒
May I ask the big theme song played by this bacteria
請問這個細菌玩的大題曲
where is its comment dafabe
它的評論大發會在哪裡
I'm about to start talking a little bit
我就要開始講一點點聲音
Because I actually study
因為我其實學物裡
Also very interested in music
對音樂也非常有興趣
so let me explain
所以我就跟大家解釋一下
Everyone in Taiwan is playing the piano at home
大家台灣在家裡玩鋼琴
what's up with this math
這個數學是怎麼回事
What is written on the piano is
鋼琴上面寫的就是
That precious man you call it LAL
那個寶人你把它說LAL
This standard IWC standard tone
這個標準 萬國標準音
maybe 440
可能就是440
Everyone has heard of A440
A440 大家都聽過
A440 means
A440的意思就是
Your ears are covered with air like this
你的耳末被空氣這樣子
When pressing 444 times per second
每一秒鐘壓444次的時候
you hear the sound
你就聽到了音力
If there is absolute pitch
如果有絕對音感
You'll say that's LAL
你就會說那個是LAL
This is what LAL on the piano means
鋼琴上面的LAL就是這個意思
there was a very important musical discovery
那有一個很重要的音樂的發現
I think it's a very important discovery
我覺得是一個非常重要的發現
The meaning of my pronunciation of this matter is
把這件事情我打讀音的意思就是
The previous one, the high-pitched one, the rate is lower than that
上一個啦,高音的啦,跟它這些費率就差了
double, 800%
兩倍,800%
Then how to divide it, find out that there is an interesting way to divide it
那這當中怎麼樣分,把它就發現說有一個有趣的分法
The result of this division is to divide it into 12 semitones
這樣分的結果呢,就是又把它分成12分半音
Then the result is that the zero of 12 is 0, and then it is
然後結果這個是,12的零是0,然後就是
Here is 1, 1 multiplied by the fold, and then this 1 is corrected
這邊就是1,1乘以折,然後這個1給個對過來
Then we see it here, Masto
那我們這邊看到就,馬斯都
like this, go around
就這樣子,繞過來
That's just right, if it's four semitones
那剛剛好,如果這有四個半音的時候
Well, I can't think that these two sounds are vibrato, which seems to be quite harmonious
那個,沒法會覺得這個兩個音就是抖音這邊好像蠻和諧的
So it will be more harmonious, then why is it more harmonious
所以會更和諧,那為什麼會更和諧
It's because Douyin is so clean
是因為,抖音是這樣的乾淨呢
This number, very accurate calculation, the result is just about 5 to 4
這個數字,很精準的細算,結果剛好差不多是5比4
Then you sound a lot, that is, there is a voice that is
那你聽起來就很多一些,就是有一個聲音是
When I pressed five times, I pressed another four times, and it went smoothly.
壓了五下的時候,另外壓了四下,就很順
What's more smooth is that the roots are collected, one is pressed twice, and the other is pressed three times
更順的是,保根收,有一個壓兩下,另外一個壓三下
three to two
有三比二
The smoothest and smoothest are four hundred and four and eight hundred and eight, exactly two pairs
最順最順的是,四百四跟八百八,剛好兩對
I hit it once, and you hit it twice. In this way, everyone feels that the chorus sound is very, very
我打一下,你們打兩下,這樣的話大家覺得這合音都跟都就是非常非常
Therefore, a series of phenomena
所以,很多壹列現象
In fact, what they are talking about is a frequency, and what they are talking about is resonance.
其實都在講的就是一個頻率,講的都是靠的就是共振
or frequency these relationships
或是定頻這些關係
So, today I hope to use such a method to tell you
所以,我今天就希望用這樣一個方式來跟大家代入說
I’m in the manager, and I’m trying to tell everyone what’s going on with Xi Jinping’s voice
我在經理,在跟大家強要講的,說習近平的聲音到底是怎麼回事
We're going back to ask him
我們就在回頭要問他說
That Ma Yoyo's
那馬悠悠的那個
please
請
Why our ears are used to hearing, we all know that the frequency of our ears may be about
為什麼我們耳朵習慣聽的,大家都知道我們耳朵的頻率聽的可能大概
560 to 560 thousand or if someone doesn't want to listen, don't listen
560到560千或是有人不要聽的不要聽
What's the best frequency?
頻率大概是哪個棒的
There is actually a very simple reason for this
這個其實有一個非常簡單的道理
It's about our body
就是跟我們身材有關
Because the number of depths per second in the air is 330 meters per second
因為深數每秒鐘在空氣裡面是每秒鐘走330公尺
Everyone has heard of this junior high school
這個初中大家都聽過
if there is a thing
如果有一個東西
Its height and length have a resonance gun when the height reaches 1 meter
它高度長度有一個共振槍高度到1公尺的時候
Its frequency is 330
它的頻率就是330
It approaches 440 people every 30 meters
它每30公尺跟440人接近
almost there
差不多就在那邊
So many people like the general policeman
所以很多喜歡大體警人
he is very comfortable
他聽得非常舒服
It's not just ears
這也是不是只有耳朵
his whole body is comfortable
他的全身都很舒服
Because he resonates with this resonant gun
因為他跟這個共振槍全部共振起來
i'm done talking
我已經就講完了
Because Toddler Ma and Tomorrow I are both 1 meter tall
因為馬幼兒跟明日我的身高都是1公尺
The depth is about 330
深數是330左右
So our ears are a natural evolutionary process
所以我們的耳朵就在自然演化過程當中
Just 430
就430
Because this is about one or two hundred hertz on average
因為這個平均大概一兩百赫茲
The average amount needs to be in the range of Hertz to several thousand
平均的額要拿赫茲一直到幾千的這個範圍
For example, when singing very high-pitched
比如說唱蠻高音的時候
He is going to put the resonance river on the small top of the head
他就要把共振江往頭頂上的小小的
The younger he is, the higher the average is, the level of resonance in Zhenjiang
越小他平均就越高共振江的平階道
So what should the average be in the Xijing area?
所以細菁大地區應該平均是多少
Did you raise your hand when you were a child?
小時候你舉手了不
do you know the answer
你知道答案嗎
That's a million times more
就是多了一百萬倍
Because Xijing's body size is a million times different from ours
因為細菁跟我們的身材就差了一百萬倍
So he's a million times taller on average
所以他平均就高了一百萬倍
So if Xijing plays his cello
所以如果細菁演奏他的大提琴
Of course we can't hear
我們當然都聽不到
If this molecule is playing
如果是這個分子在演奏
When this molecule plays his cello
這個分子在演奏他的大提琴的時候
that would be another point
那就會又差一個點了
Because of the size of the molecule
因為這分子的大小
It is ten to ten times worse than ours.
就是比我們差的是十的十次光對來一級的
So the average is higher again
所以平均就又更高了
That's why
也就是因為這樣子
So of course we can't hear
所以我們當然不可能聽到
The voice of Wenzi and Molecule
文子跟分子的聲音
We know that the principle is actually quite similar
我們知道它的原理其實是相當類似的
We just figured out a way to secretly convert it
我們就想一辦法來偷偷地把它轉化之後
see if we can hear
看我們能不能聽得到
This is how I think about bacteria from a human with atoms and molecules
這就是我怎麼從一個就原子跟分子人來想細菌
Bacteria, I can tell you very clearly this time
細菌我這次就可以很清楚跟大家講
What I call the sound of bacteria
我所謂實在細菌的聲音
It's actually a molecule from bacteria
其實是來自細菌的分子
how often they vibrate
它們振動的頻率
if i could hear
我如果有辦法聽到的話
I know what molecules the bacteria emit
我就知道細菌散發出來是什麼分子
what kind of taste are those molecules
那些分子是有什麼樣的品味
Or the concept of taste or sound is like this
或是味道或是聲音的概念是這樣子
ok
ok
I speak a little fast
我講的有一點點快
So if you want to know more details
所以如果大家想要知道更細的話
It's okay to interrupt me
不妨就打斷我沒關係
Okay, so we're going to see how to listen to this now.
好那我們現在就要看怎麼去聽這件事情
This is the comparison I'm going to talk about today
這個我今天要講的比較
Scientifically speaking, slowing down the valley of light sounds scary
科學上的說法就是拉慢光谷聽起來就很可怕
This is an Indian scientist who won the Nobel Prize in 1930, the Physics Prize
這個是一個印度科學家,1930年拿到諾德爾獎,物理獎
He is all Asian, the first Asian to win the Nobel Prize in Science
他是全亞洲人,第一個亞洲人拿到科學的諾德爾獎
so i was probably very young and i only got the nodel prize
所以我大概非常年輕,我只有拿到諾德爾獎
He did some very simple experiments himself in India, it sounds simple
他自己在印度做的一些非常簡單的實驗,聽起來很簡單
Then published a magazine article in 1928 now called the shock number no one knows how much
然後在1928年發表一篇現在叫做衝擊數沒有人知道的雜誌文章是多少
No one listened to it, no one didn’t know much about it, and there was an article about two or three years later that he won the Nobel Prize
沒有人聽,沒有人大家都不特別了解,有一個文章大概兩三年之後他就拿諾德爾獎
He proved that resources are very simple, that is, he took some scales, and there was also a yellow light
他證明了資源很簡單的一件事,就是他拿一些撥鱗片,也是有黃光
What can be green-yellow is also green-red, and it can be turned green
可以綠黃光的也是綠紅光,可以把它綠掉的
Then he proved one thing, that is, the light, the reason why the light sees different colors is because the screen is different
然後他就證明一件事情,就是說光線,光線之所以看到不同的顏色是因為它屏幕不一樣
Don't say that hearing without red light is better
不要說沒有人紅光的聽力就比較好
slower, lower
比較慢一點的,比較低一點的
The frequency of blue light is higher
那藍光的頻率就比較高
The frequency of the blue light is just a little brighter.
那藍光的頻率就正明一點
When I use a light mirror like this
我用一個這樣的光鏡鏡的時候
when the light mirror
那個光鏡鏡的時候
There are very, very small light mirrors
有非常非常的小的光鏡
it's time to come out
是散出來的時候
it will run out with a yellow light
它會用黃光跑出來
Then it is clear about this matter
那它就正明了這件事情
so it writes this article
所以它寫了這個文章
Then later when it was explained like this
然後後來這樣子就解釋的時候
why is this
為什麼會這樣
Because there are some molecules in it
因為裡面有一些分子
After those molecules are excited by this light wave,
那些分子被這個光波激發了之後
Take that molecule as if dialing that emotion
就把那個分子就好像撥那個情
it vibrates
它就震盪起來
The frequency of the light at the time of the shock
那一震的時候那個光線的頻率
just give it that frequency
就把那個頻率給它
Then the light only has its own frequency
然後光就只好自己的頻率
just lost a little bit
就損失了一點點
so it was supposed to be aura
所以它本來是靈光
then dropped a little bit
然後就降了一點點
become light and run out
變成光光跑出來
That's right, let's talk about this matter.
那正明這件事情就拿到那個來講
So I tell many classmates every time I talk about this time
所以我就跟很多的同學每次講到這個時候
Everyone is a star
人家都很明星
very angry
很大一氣
that person got one
那個人拿到一個
Just have a sun light, then the landscape mirror, and then take a few pieces of that rotten glass
隨便有一個太陽光,然後那個風光鏡,然後拿幾片那個爛玻璃
That's the proof that if Li Guang goes in and yellow light comes out, he will take the captain
就是那個證明說,立光進去有黃光出來就拿那個隊長
Why spend so much money on central research like this
為什麼花那麼多錢給中央研究這樣
Then you have to explain this more profoundly, which probably means that it is called a
那這個你要解釋的更深刻,大概就是說它叫做一個
For every molecule it actually has one like a resonance gun
每一個分子它其實有一個就像一個共振槍一樣
then it starts to oscillate, it has a frequency it likes
那它開始會震盪,它有一個它喜歡的頻率
When you send in a light, when you excite this thing
那你送進來的一個光線的時候,你把它激發的這個東西的時候
This light will lose a little frequency, which happens to be
這個光線就會損失一點的頻率,那個頻率剛好就是
It likes this and that frequency, so as long as you see this, you will know
它喜歡這個那個頻率,所以你只要珍珍到這個你就知道說
There is a musical instrument inside, and that musical instrument emits this frequency
裡面有一個這個樂器,那個樂器就釋發這種頻率
Then this kind of thing can enable you to be called vibration spectrum
那這種東西可以讓你能夠才叫做震動光譜
Then we generally say that it just thinks about life.
那我們一般的說法就是它就是想生命就對了
The frequency of direct life is very, very high, we can't even hear it
直度生命的頻率非常非常的高,我們都聽不到說
What we're relying on is a laser light going in
我們要仰賴的是一個雷射光進去
Then let it come out and see how much it becomes, let's measure how much it becomes
然後讓它出來就看它變得多少,我們去量它變得多
How much will know the instrument that I measured
多少就知道說被我量的那一個樂器
The instrument that I talked about a lot
被我聊多起來那個樂器
its resonant frequency
它的共振的頻率
What is the vibration frequency it likes
它喜歡的這個振動頻率是多少
This is the whole story
這整個就是這樣的一個故事
What about Mr. Raban?
那這個拉斑先生呢
Just invented this Laban public servant, and there are also very fast
就發明了這個拉斑公僕也有很快的
So I get it in two or three years when I have a few
所以我少數的時候兩三年就拿到
what you dreamed of and got it at such a young age
你夢想的而且這麼年輕就拿到
If you want to look carefully
那如果要仔細的看
Clearer young people are like
比較清楚一點的年輕人就是像
Let's say now this is a molecule
比方說現在這就是一個分子
This molecule probably
這分子大概
Only the vice president can read it
副院長才唸得出來
Because I am your declaration
因為我是你宣理
I don't even know what this molecule is called
我更不知道這分子叫什麼什麼
I just know it's some carbon, cream, green
我只知道它有些碳、奶油、青
Then this one looks like a flasher
那這個這樣看起來就像一個開閃的
there is a vibration pattern
就有一個振動的模式
it opens like a flash
它就像一個閃的那樣開
Then there's one that likes to vibrate
那這有一個它喜歡振動的
So for each molecule it has
所以每一個分子它有
it vibrates in different places
它有不同的地方在振動
For example, this carbon heel
比方說這個碳跟
Large, with carbon and oxygen
大、有碳跟氧
it has one like this
它就有一個喜歡這樣子
It seems to be stretched like this
好像伸縮的這樣一個
each of these has a pattern
那這每一個都有一個模式
Then they all have their own vibration frequency
那它們都有它自己的振動頻率
so which molecule is over there
所以哪一個分子在那邊
Who wants to take his time
哪一個人希望照他的時候
You will measure several frequencies
你就會量到有好幾個頻率
Yes, then you can analyze his different frequencies and you will know.
是 那你就去分析他這個不同的頻率你就知道
use him as a fingerprint
就把他當作指紋
you know what molecule
你就知道大概是什麼分子
like say you listen if your ears are really good
就像說你聽如果你耳朵非常好
you listen to a good piano
你聽一打很好的琴
He or you listen to different instruments
他或是你聽不同的樂器
You can tell what kind of instrument that is when you hear it
你聽你就知道那可是什麼樂器
It's the same reason
跟這個道理是一樣的
So we borrow the concept
所以我們就借用這樣的概念
Treat that tone like a music garden
把那個音色就像是一個音樂園一樣
then we maybe
然後我們也許
If you can hear the sound from bacteria
如果能夠聽到從來自細菌的聲音的時候
we can go back and say
我們就可以去反推說
this may be some bacteria
這也許是什麼細菌
Or the more interesting thing I want to talk about is to say
或者是真正我要講的比較有趣的是說
Then if this bacterium is attacked by others,
那這個細菌如果被人家攻擊的時候
For example, like being us
比方說像被我們
we call it the idiot antibiotic
我們把它叫做癡抗生素
From a bacterial point of view
對於從細菌的角度來看
They were poisoned by us, right?
就是被我們下毒嘛 對不對
our miserable
我們那個慘
When everyone starts to kill
大家開始下毒手的時候
defense of bacteria
細菌的防衛的時候
then he may emit molecules
那他就可能散出分子
or his skin is peeled off by you
或是他的皮被你剝掉
or what these molecules
或什麼這些分子
can we measure them
我們是不是能夠量到他們的
at a vibrational frequency
在一個振動頻率
then we will know
那我們就知道
change the voice of bacteria
改字細菌的聲音
That's the story I'm going to tell today
這就是我今天要講的故事
OK
OK
how to do this
怎麼去做到這件事情
This frequency change is clearly coordinated in this place
這個頻率的改變就在很清楚就協調在這個地方
that's not the case
那不這樣
If I notice here that there are some real experts
如果在這我注意到有一些真的專家
they are fast asleep
他們已經快睡著了
heard here already said
聽到這裡已經講說
So my elementary school here already knows
所以我這邊小學已經知道了
i'm still here this
我還在這裡這個
It's okay if you start typing
你請你開始打個點沒關係
don't mind too much
不要太介意
Because I'm not talking about you
因為我講對象不是針對你
good
好
Ramek's light stock is actually very good
拉麥光股其實非常好
What is the most useful Lame light stock?
拿來最有用的拉麥光股是什麼
in the quiz
在測驗
test
測驗
that
那個
would you be sir or
你會先生或者是
when your boyfriend proposes to you
你男朋友跟你求婚的時候
is it true
是不是很真實的
he took that diamond
他拿那個鑽石
Then drill it for you like this
然後就給你鑽這樣
I bought an 80 carat diamond to propose to you
我買了個80克拉的鑽石要跟你求婚
Then you see how it is possible
那你看說怎麼可能嘛
How is it possible for your salary
對你這個薪水怎麼可能
how to check
那怎麼去檢驗
diamond
鑽石
No
沒有
From a chemical point of view, even if it is the same as coal, it is charcoal
成化學的角度,縱使跟煤炭是一樣,都是炭
If you go to propose to him and take a piece of charcoal, do you take one?
如果你去跟他求婚,拿了一塊炭,你拿一個沒有
My love is so real, then throw it in the fire and burn it
我的愛就這麼真實,然後就把丟到火裡燒掉
Then you took him a very shiny one, it may be a Soviet
那你跟他拿了一個很亮晶晶的一個,那可能是蘇聯傳
what do you do then what do you do
那你怎麼辦呢?你怎麼辦法?
This chemistry is...
這化學分是...
what is this? i don't know, it won't make a strange sound
這什麼東西?我不知道,不會有很奇怪的聲音
So this...
那所以這個...
How to test it, diamonds and Shi Nuo are the same
怎麼樣去測說,鑽石跟石諾也都是一樣是
It's all charcoal, or just plain...
都是炭,或是平常的...
There is a very simple way to talk about coal or something
大家一般講的那個煤炭或什麼的,有一個很簡單的方式
It is the two big drawing boards, although their materials are all charcoal
就是兩大拉板光,雖然他們的材料都是炭
But the arrangement of their atoms is different
但他們原子的排法是不一樣的
Then the arrangement is different, resulting in this action
那這個排法不一樣,就造成這行動
The same material, when making a different feeling, its frequency is different
同樣的材料,做不同的一個情的時候,它的頻率是不一樣
so your boyfriend gave you a diamond
所以你男朋友給你一個鑽石
you bring it is the first thing you take it
你拿來就是第一件事情就把它拿到
Then you break the switch
那你拉斷關主一下
once frequently wrong
一旦頻密錯了
OK
好不好
That's it for next time
那個下次再拿好了這樣子
Actually we have some legislators
其實我們有一些立法人
When visiting our office
到我們所裡面去參觀的時候
Let's just tell him we'll do this
我們就跟他講我們會做這件事情
That's a female legislator
那是女性的立法人
What we care most about is not whether our experiments are done well or not.
最關心的並不是我們實驗做的好不好
Is his diamond really like this?
是他那個鑽石到底是真的這樣
I want to say you can tell the name
我想說可以講名字的喔
in this way
這樣子
Then of course you see
那這樣你看當然就說
That's because it's very easy to use recently.
那因為最近拉斷關主就是非常好用
Pull off the master's pull off
拉斷關主的拉斷
Except for that
除了測說那個
advanced is not really love me outside
先進是不是真的愛我之外
and many other uses
還有很多其他的用途
various materials
各種不同的材料
you can hear his voice clearly
你都可以清聽他的聲音
Then you can tell
然後你就可以判別
take him as a fingerprint
把他當做指紋
You can use it for many tests
你就可以拿來做很多的檢驗
but pull off the master
可是拉斷關主
just after coming out
剛出來之後呢
have similar grades
有差不多成績
In the 1970s and 1980s
七八十年的時候
actually very painful
其實非常痛苦
Why
為什麼
There is an important reason to say
有重要的原因就是說
Pull off the signal of the master
拉斷關主的訊號
very very small
非常非常小
Everyone probably knows Fluorescent
大家也許都知道螢光
Everyone in the fluorescent family has
螢光家人大家都有
It looks like Li Yujun's
很像李玉君的那個
In fact, there is a fluorescent light in the middle
其實中間有一個螢光
Fluorescent itself is easy to light up
螢光本身是很容易亮起來的
that light
那個光
I just told you about the Valley of Rahman Optics
我剛剛跟妳講說拉曼光谷
It's up to me to type a document to get in.
是要靠我打一光件進去
Then it came out very hot
然後出來很微熱
very slightly hot
很微熱的一點點
colored light
變得顏色的光
this thing to detect
這件事來偵測
often before
常常以前
I told the teacher who is Raman Optics Valley
跟做拉曼光谷的老師都有說
ok then you can go
好 那你能就去
Go to the Yangliang thing
去對陽亮這個東西
and put it in
然後就把它放進去
Then the students will go skating on the mountain
然後學生就要山上去滑
The student will come back in three days
學生三天以後回來
The Optics Valley just came out a little bit
那個光谷才出來一點點
Because that signal is very, very slightly hot
因為就是那個信號非常非常的微熱
16 orders of magnitude worse than cloud light
跟雲光比起來差的16個數量級
I just said that the earth is 6 orders of magnitude different from us
我剛剛講過地球跟我們是差6個數量級
This Raman Optical Valley is 16 orders of magnitude different from Yunguang
這個拉曼光谷跟雲光差的16個數量級
That difference of 10 orders of magnitude becomes
那差10個數量級就變成是說
It's so quiet I can't hear you at all
就靜悄悄完全聽不到了
sounds like
聽起來啊
I can hear you
講起來是聽得到了
Then it won't be talked about since people got it
然後不會自從人家拿到都有講
because it's useless
因為就沒什麼用
Because it is difficult to do this experiment
因為就是很難做這個實驗
in 1974
在1974年的時候
there is a very
有一個非常
change of interest
興趣性的變化
at the University of West Germany
就在西德大學
especially professors they are doing
尤其是教授他們在做
accidental discovery
意外的發現
you are going to detect
你要去偵測
Here they do a
這裡面他們做的是一個
molecular
分子
They're going to measure the molecule's short ad
他們要去量這個分子的拉短廣告
Turns out they put it in a
結果他們把它放在一個
surface of a plume
一片羽泥的表面上面
The results of it
結果呢
What about the surface of the feather mud?
羽泥的表面呢
happens to be rough
剛好是很粗糙的
The results of it
結果呢
Suddenly exploded by 1 million times
突然爆漲了100萬倍
Exploded 1 million times
爆漲了100萬倍
1 million times is to suddenly put feather mud
100萬倍就是突然把羽泥
down to the size of the earth
下遍地球這個大
super scary
超嚇人
because it is on a surface
因為是在一個表面上面
So this phenomenon is called
所以這個現象就叫做
surface enhancement
表面增強
shorten the ad
拉短廣告
Because people call it Surface Enhanced
因為人家叫做Surface Enhanced
Abbreviated as Surge
簡稱叫做Surge
wait a minute we'll see a lot of words
等一下我們會看到很多字
S-E-R-S is such a thing
S-E-R-S就是這樣一件事情
Everyone who suffers from the phenomenon of Surge
Surge這個現象的大家就
wow many people
哇 很多人
I thought this could find him
就覺得這能夠去找他
why on earth
到底是為什麼
Why can be enhanced a million times
為什麼可以增強一百萬倍
Some even enhanced to that meaning times
甚至有人增強到那個意義倍
or something
或什麼之類
that's it
就是這樣子
At the beginning of 1970, the big circle was big
1970年年初大圈大
it's been 40 years
已經40年了
I solemnly declare here
我在這邊很鄭重的宣布
The most detailed reason
真正最細節的原因
Why can it be enhanced to so much
為什麼可以增強到那麼多
From theory to experiment
從理論到實驗
issues that have not yet been fully resolved
都還沒有完全解決的問題
This question is a
這個問題是一個
still a still ongoing party center
還是一個還在進行黨中心
Even if everything is as good as we are now
即便是我們現在這麼好的一切
But that detail in that
但是那個裡面的那個細節
so many male protagonists
那他很多的男主
I can't even talk here today
我今天都沒有辦法在這邊講
but i want to tell you
不過我要跟大家講
The person who discovered this phenomenon
當初這個發現這現象的人
Some people think they've been dreaming about him
有人認為就一直夢想著他
that should be in his lifetime
那個應該在他有生之年
will get that to talk like this
會拿到那個要講這樣
I think he probably doesn't have much hope
我看他大概希望不是很大
that I know like this
那個我認識的這樣
that would be a very interesting phenomenon
那會是一個非常有趣的現象
But I don't agree that a thing can be enhanced to a million to a billion times
但是一下子不認同一個事情可以增強到百萬到億倍
something like this is a big deal
這樣的東西是一個天大地大的事情
Just like when the money in your pocket suddenly increases by a billion times
就像你口袋的錢如果突然增加了億倍的時候
you are very very excited like this
你就非常非常興奮這樣子
That's certainly an interesting phenomenon
那這個當然是一個有趣的現象
But it starts directly from the details
可是它到底從直接從細節到底
It is the electromagnetic factory
就是電磁廠
Because laser light is an electromagnetic factory
因為雷射光就是一個電磁廠
Then why is it like this
然後為什麼會是這樣子
And then what exactly is the molecule that is adsorbed on the surface of this silver
然後分子到底是什麼吸附在這個銀的表面上
so what's under this arrangement
那又什麼在這種安排底下
it will have such a large signal enhancement
它就會有這麼大的信號的增強
This is how the details of each film require lucky scientific research
這就是每一部的細節都需要很幸運的科學研究
Then we have been doing it until now
那我們也到現在一直在做
but i want to tell you again
但是我要再跟你講
Although we don't fully understand its rationale
我們雖然不完全了解它的道理
But we can still use
但是我們還是可以拿來用
It's like saying I don't understand what violin sentiment is all about
就像說我完全不了解小提琴的民情是什麼做
But it has to be about the fact that I can't play the violin
可是它必須講是我不能來拉小提琴的這件事情
is the same reason
是同樣的道理
so it's for you
所以它是有為你的進術
but really
但是呢 真正的
So from the most primitive principle, we still don't have a special understanding
所以從最原始的原理我們還不是特別的了解
Although we have about 80% or 90% understanding, it is already good
雖然我們有大概八九成的了解都已經不錯了
But those last few areas hopefully we can go on in my lifetime
但是最後的那幾領域希望在我有生之年我們可以走得下去
This two-sided, this Laren light map, this phenomenon
這個兩面這條拉倫光圖這個現象
In 1974, it was red for about ten years before it became a plated
在1974年紅了大概十年左右就變得一鍍
Just because they can't go on
就因為都一直接不下去
that's great
那就很成績
It's that they have probably changed their careers in those years.
就是那些年大概都已經改行了
By 1997
到了1997年的時候
There is a scholar named Nie Shuning who went to the United States from mainland China
有一位叫聶淑寧中國大陸去美國的學者
Nie Shuning
叫聶淑寧教授
This article he published in Science
他在Science發表的這篇文章
This article has probably been cited 3,000 times so far
這文章到目前為止可能已經被引誡三千次了
Because this is tantamount to the renaissance movement of surface-enhanced full-light maps
因為這等於是說表面增強拉滿光圖的文藝復興運動
Thirty years later, I suddenly published this article again
三十年之後突然又發了這個文章
He did a very interesting experiment
他做了一個非常有趣的實驗
When I was just drawing with him
我剛剛跟他圖的時候
We've got the rough surface when we're here today
我們今天來已經弄的表面很粗糙的時候
What happened after Ke Zhi appeared?
柯智出現之後呢
Don't use this to corrode
大家不要用這個去腐蝕
he's in trouble
他有些麻煩
I don't know if I said it
不知道有沒有講過
Let's just make some rice
我們就乾脆做一些賴米
particles of silver
銀的顆粒
just hit one by one
就一顆一顆的打
and sprinkle it on the surface
然後就把它撒在表面上面
then measure this
然後就去量這個
Enhance the signal of Optics Valley?
增強光谷的訊號是不是
Then he did it
那他也就做了這件事情
Then he took that Optics Valley
那他就把那個光谷就
That's the one
就是那個
It's just gold particles sprinkled on it.
就是金的粒子就撒上去了
and then what
然後接著呢
He hit a light on it
他就打了一顆光上去
Particle shot in
粒光打進去
Then I saw you talking about particle light shooting in
然後我看你講說粒光打進去
The words of Raman Kwang
那拉曼光的話就是
yellow light running out
黃光跑出來
That's either Raman light or it's reflected back
那不是拉曼光就是反射回來
It's the particles of light that go in and the particles of light come out, right?
就是粒光進去 粒光出來對不對
Well, you can see this small picture
好了這個小圖就看到
Because most of it is grain light going in and grain light coming out
因為大部分都是粒光進去 粒光出來
there are a lot of
就是有一大堆的
Granules of Lamikin
賴米金的顆粒
In the end, I saw two or three
結果最後看到兩三顆是
yellowish
發黃光的
Then this article becomes a
那這個文章就變成是一個
very very interesting discovery
非常非常有趣的發現
So everyone thought
所以以前大家以為說
That is, we tore 10,000 pieces
就是我們撕了一萬個
that that that
那個那個
This light source goes down and cries
這個光源下去哭
Once we can, everyone will work hard to prop up the signal into a million times, and each person will share a hundred times
一旦能大家都會努力,把信號撐起來變成一百萬倍,每人分一百倍
It turns out that there are only three people who are actually working. What is the consciousness? Those three people are police officers.
結果發現真正在做工只有三個人,意識是什麼?那三個人是差人
This phenomenon is called the discovery that even if the surface is enhanced and recovered
這個現象就叫做發現即使表面增強光復這個現象
In the past 30 years, I didn’t know anything about it. There were some very, very HOT people in it.
以前30年其實也不了解,裡面有一些非常非常HOT的人
It is called HOTSBOT, which is a very hot hot zone, and it still contributes 5-60% of the real contribution
就是叫做HOTSBOT,就是很熱的熱區,還是真正貢獻的5-60%
The other tens of thousands of people only contribute the other 5-60%
其他幾萬人都只有貢獻另外的5-60%
So this is called the concept of a very hot hot zone, which is the hot spot of HOTSBOT
所以這個就叫做一個非常熱的熱區的概念,就是HOTSBOT的熱點
That’s why I’m gradually starting to talk about what my research has to do with this matter.
那這個就是我開始漸漸要開始談一些我的研究跟這件事有什麼關係
I will comment here first, and talk about the original problem
我就在這裡先評一下下,講到這個原本問題
I see that there are not many people who go to bed early
我看睡覺睡早的人還沒有很多在那裡
So I'm actually more and more confident
所以我其實還越講越有信心
Teacher you just said that
老師你剛才說那個
440 that voice that pulls
440那個拉的那個音
Is his higher octave 888
他的高八度是888嗎
What about an octave lower?
那低八度呢
an octave lower is that frequency
低八度是那個頻率
This except 2
這除了2
So he's a 2 speed
所以他就是一個2的極速
Then his contribution is to say
那他的貢獻就是說
why did you find this
為什麼你找這支
if you can't cut it
你如果不能把它切開來
i can't turn around
我就不能轉掉
do you know
大家知道嗎
that's what i say
就是我把它講
the thought of cutting it into 12 semitones
那想到要把它切成12個半音
Then there is a semitone between the eight and the close
然後那個八跟收之間是半音
Then there is a semitone between C and D
然後那個C跟D之間是半音
Total like this plus
總共就這樣子加
The result
湊出來的結果
just so close
剛剛好很接近
There will be an extra charge
會有一個多跟收
There's also the matter of multi-tracking
還有多跟音這件事情
Then his ears heard
然後他的耳朵都聽出來
Well, I've actually met people with that kind of absolute pitch.
那其實我遇過那種絕對音感的人
they hate it
他們是非常痛恨吧
because what he wants is
因為他要的是
I just said 3 to 2
我剛剛講的是3比2
he wants to be like a mathematician
他要像數學家一樣
Accurate 3 to 2, it can hear the difference
精準的3比2,它是聽得出來那個差別的
Just now I told you that it was 1.4987
剛剛我跟妳講是那個是1.4987
If the ratio is 3 to 2, it is not 1.5.
那個比例3比2的話不是1.5吧
That's 1.4987, isn't it one thousandth of a difference?
那是1.4987,是不是差1千分之1的
It's almost audible at all frequencies.
就是差一點點的頻率它都聽得出來
So if you listen, well I hear Acapella
所以妳如果去聽,好我聽到Akapela
Last night I went to the National Concert Hall was Akapela
昨天晚上我到國家音樂廳是Akapela
Many masters there are real
那裡面很多的高手是真的
when we get along very, very, very well
合得非常非常非常好的時候
Not the sounds on the piano
並不是鋼琴上面的音發
because I'm always 440
因為我常常是440
I am not the frequency of 4401
我不是4401這個頻率
I am 4401.5, so any frequency is fine
我是4401.5,所以哪一個頻率都可以
So these are selected
所以這些都是選出來
Once selected, the other sounds seem to be non-existent to you
那一旦選了之後其他音就好像對妳為是不存在的
But the sound of 4401 means of course
可是4401的音這個當然是說
Wait a minute, I'm finally going to broadcast the sound of that bacteria to you
等一下終於要播那個細菌的聲音給妳們聽
I say that because you are digitally generated
我說那音就是因為妳是用數字產生出來
So you want me to put a pattern
所以妳又要我播一個圖案
I'll wait until I play a 723 frequency for you to listen to
我等下我播一個什麼723的頻率的給妳聽
OK
OK
there are other problems
還有別的問題
If not
沒有的話
It seems that everyone is still maintaining the status quo
看起來大家還有維持顯個狀況
I'll just keep talking
我就繼續講下去
we just want to say
我們就想說
after some research
經過一番研究
found that those hot spots
發現說那些熱點
what is it actually
其實是什麼樣
looks like
看起來
you thought
你以為說
here is a bright spot
這邊叫一個亮點
It is because the optical display resolution is not enough
是因為光學顯示解析度不夠
really those hot spots
真正那些很熱的點
It's actually two atoms of gold.
其實是兩顆金的原子
it's very very close
它靠得非常非常的近
that in optical display
那在光學顯示
These particles of gold that I'm going to talk about
我要講的這些金的粒子
Size is 25 Nie Camp
大小是25耐營
I just forgot to mention one thing
我剛剛忘了講一件事情
What are we usually used to
我們平常有什麼習慣的
For example filter
比方說濾光
wavelength
波長
is the fluctuation of the wave
就是波的波動
Like the waves of the ocean the long way this wave goes
就像海浪這個波的長路
The filter is about 550 or so
濾光是大概有550左右
It is 550 Naiying
就是550耐營
So we're doing camping now
所以我們現在在做耐營
It's better than that wave
可以去都是比那個波的
10 times less frequent
頻率要小10倍
or 20 times as small
或是20倍那麼小
so we make that light
所以我們做那個燈
Just a little big beach to see
就有點大海灘去看
The fluctuation of the wave of the ocean is one meter.
海浪的浪的波動就是一公尺這樣一直過來
When we reach the shore, if it is a sandy beach with accidental rocks
到了岸邊的時候如果是偶然石的沙灘
The person who accidentally stoned one by one fell
那偶然石一顆一顆的人所以就著
The waves hit the small stones by the sea
那個浪打在海邊的小石頭上
Those little stones are using this metaphor
那些小石頭就是用這個比喻來講
These are the small stones that we are making at Nini Technology
就是我們耐尼科技在做的那些小石頭
That wave hits like a light wave
那個浪就光波這樣打過來
550 Nini is hit on a particle of tens of Nini
550耐尼打在一個幾十耐尼的顆粒上面
is such a game
就是這樣一個遊戲
Because our Naini technology has now advanced to
因為我們的耐尼科技現在已經進步到了
It’s not ideal yet, but it’s already possible to be Shi Nai Ni
還沒有理想但是已經是可以做石耐尼左右
Well done here
這邊做得還蠻不錯的
Then we just have to find a way to agree
那我們就是要去想辦法說好
Since it is like this
那既然是這樣子
Are we going to be able to do a bunch of Nenny examples?
我們是不是能夠來做一堆的耐尼例子
Then they get very close
然後他們之間就靠得很近
So everyone is hot in the middle
所以中間大家都很熱
In that case, wouldn't the signal be amplified even more?
那這樣的話那個信號不就放大了更多嗎
That's when I was a student in the master's class of the Physics Department of National Taiwan University with me.
那就是當初我跟我一個台大物理系碩士班的學生
gave advice
給了建議
It's a long story because I've actually been doing this for almost a decade
故事很長,因為我實際上這件事做了將近十年的時間
I'm not here to spend time telling stories
我就不在這邊花時間去講故事
But this young man was very interesting, so he said yes
但是這個年輕人非常有意思,他就說好
We actually just happened to have a senior working on this material
我們實際上剛好有一個學長在做這個材料
This material is here, many first-time students can do it by themselves when they go home.
這個材料在這邊很多初登同學回家都可以自己去做
This, everyone said that selling Mi Technology sounds very difficult
這個,大家都說這個賣米科技聽起來很困難
How to do Mimi Technology, in fact, it sounds very simple
要怎麼做賣米科技,其實相對的聽起來就是非常簡單
When you get home, go buy a battery
你到家裡就去買一個電池
Then you make a little acid, then leave the acid or muddy acid
然後你就弄一點酸,然後留酸或是泥泥酸
Or a little bit of acetic acid, which is safer
或是比較安全一點點的醋酸也可以
So stainless steel, another piece of aluminum
所以不鏽鋼,另外就把一片鋁
Aluminum is usually at home, and the aluminum box puts it here
鋁就是平常在家裡,鋁盒子就把它放到這邊去
Then add this battery here, then add it, and then it starts to clear
然後這邊加這個電池,然後加上去,然後它就開始冒清
Then after taking the risk, you thought it would be difficult
然後冒完之後,你以為就很難
very expensive machine
很昂貴的機器
This is why everyone should support the central research
這是為什麼要大家好好支持中央研究
you have expensive machines
你有要很昂貴的機器
you can take this picture
你才能照到這個照片
just become money
就是變成錢而已
you didn't see say
你很沒看到說
it turns out that
原來那個
if there is not
如果沒有
you see nothing happened to us
你看到我們什麼事也沒發生
It's just a woman here
就是一片女在這邊
but when you actually look
但是你真正去看的時候
It's actually full of holes like this
上面其實就布滿這樣的洞
And this is completely spontaneous
而這個是完全自發生
when you don't need a car
就是什麼時候你都不需要車
it is brought
它就是拿來
and very interesting
而且非常有趣
This is a material given in the previous part
這個是一個上一部給的材料
That
那
You see it's really just a hole
你看它真的就是一個洞
keep it in
一直裝進去
it is this
它就是這個
cut it all the way
一直切開來看
it's really
它就真的
The straight film is always put in like this
純直片就這樣一直裝進去
keep it in
一直裝進去
That
那
its pipe is
它的管子就是
This is like a room tube
這邊就像一個室管一樣
But a whole row of chamber tubes
但是一整排的室管
it keeps going in
它就一直裝進去
this is the material
這就是這個材料
so
所以
there should be a way
應該是有辦法
OK
OK
Automatically
不重自動
I should not be...
我應該不是...
they are...
他們在...
have...
有...
yesterday no...
昨天沒有...
I'm going to listen to Cappeda
我去聽打卡佩達
There is a special sound maker like this
就有一個專門在製造這個聲音的這樣
is good music
是個好音樂
music
音樂
I said you take this material
我說你拿這個材料
Then start going...
然後就開始去...
This is called...
做的這個叫做...
Shock oxidation
揚擊氧化
This is called blow oxidation treatment
這個叫做揚擊氧化處理
Oxidation of the blood vessel in the target
氧化裡的脈泥管的針對
This way I will always...
這樣子自己會一直...
go down
下去
That sound doesn't need to be too audio
那個聲音不需要太音頻
Is this okay
這樣可以嗎
Can
可以
so it's because the sound
所以是因為聲音開來
there's noise
有聲音
now he is talking
現在是他在講
or this
還是這個
So in the end, there is a shortage of funds
所以終於就缺個多經費
when i first came
我剛來的時候
some that really good one
某個那個真正的好的那個
Can't connect to a computer
一個電腦就接不上去
so wait a minute
所以等一下
We relate donations later
我們把捐款相關在後面
that's the funniest thing to say
那最有趣的是說
listen up everyone
大家聽下去
He will do this himself
這個事情他自己會
A pipe goes down vertically
一個管子垂直磚下去
This expression throughout the cycle
這在整個周期表情
only you
只有你這個人
only he is like this
只有他是這樣子
you smooth it out
你把它弄平
So there are a lot of new bricks here.
那這裡面很多的新磚都不講
anyway you have to smooth
反正你要弄平
And today we will put it
然後今天我們就把它
put it in the plug
放到栓裡面去
Then he'll grow in by himself like this
然後他就會自己這樣長進去
Then keep bricking in
然後一直磚進去
Then this brick goes in
那這個磚進去
brick into this
磚進去這個
So this ratio
所以這個比例
This ratio is easily
這個比例輕而易舉
This is like a tunnel with this pipe
就是這個像個隧道有這個管子
The length of this tunnel is compared with this pipeline
這個隧道的長度跟這個管境比起來
It is easy to do casually and it is longer than the snow mountain tunnel
輕而易舉隨便做都比雪山隧道還要長
So when you go in, you can say that my current management environment is
所以你進去你可以說我現在這個管境就是
Shimi is ready
時耐米好了
Then you need to get a 500 mic
然後你要弄個500麥克風
just wait for three days
你就等個三天
And then it turns straight in and straight
然後它就一直轉進去就直直的
just keep turning in
就一直轉進去
just put it there
就是完全那個只是把它擺在那邊
Then you're skiing again, just go skiing
然後你又該滑雪了就去滑雪
do what you should be doing
該在做什麼事就做
you are so sour
什麼事你就就那個酸
Just straight up help you do this later
就直直以後幫你做這個
That's a chemistry called itself
那就是一個化學叫做自己
self organized
self organized
a process of self-combination
就自己組合的一個過程
that's more interesting like this
那更有趣的是這樣子
If you
你如果
You find an acid that is sulfuric acid
你找到一個酸的就是硫酸
Then you tell me that I should be Yang Jizu
那你就講說我這個應該要做楊吉祖
What is the voltage of a battery
有個電池的電壓要放多少
How much did I spend a earth voltage on?
我都花了一個土電壓放多少
It will find, that is to say, you go to different acids, called zero acid, salicylic acid
它會發現,就是說你去不同的酸,叫零酸、柳酸
One thing that will happen when they are in different pressure changes is
他們在不同的變壓的時候會發生一件事情是
Even if it is lined up here, it will be neatly arranged, horizontally
連它在這上面排隊都會排得很整齊,橫向的
As long as the rows are close to each other, like this one is well-behaved
就自己排的都緊緊靠,像這個是規規矩矩
Arranged like a grid, not like the one just now
排的像一個格子一樣,不是像剛剛這一張
The row here is not so good
這裡面就排的不是那麼特別好
But in some acids, it selects its own row
但是在某一些酸裡面,它就自己選排了
And it's very, very simple, you'll make this Naimi
而且非常非常簡單,你會做這個耐米
That is, you add the transformer voltage of each frame
就是每一幅的變壓你加上去
The distance between the hole and the hole is only 2.5 meters
它這個洞跟洞之間的距離只有2.5耐米
Which means you're going back home and it's easy to get that
也就是說你要回到家裡,很容易拿到那個
You can buy a nine-panel battery with just one
隨便一根就能夠買一個九幅的電池
Bring it, it's easy about 50 yuan, 100 yuan
拿來,很容易大概50塊100塊
Then you take a little bit of acetic acid, or that
然後你就拿一點點醋酸,或是那個
that salicylic acid or something and then you put it in
那個柳酸或什麼之類的東西,然後你就把它擺進去
I probably wouldn't have acted like this back then
那時候我可能不會做出這樣子
But not so well
可是沒有排那麼好
but the distance between their average openings
但是他們平均的洞口之間的距離
It also fits this relationship
也就符合這個關係
Then it's easy to get out of that country
那就很容易就出那個國中的
Or elementary school classmates did this
或是小學生同學就做了這個
Then take it to talk to their teacher
然後就拿去跟他們老師講說
I made a nanostructure
我就做了一個奈米結構
The nanostructures are only 25 nanometers apart
那個奈米結構之間距離只有25奈米
If you don't believe me, just go and see for yourself
不信的話你就老是你自己去看一看
Then the teacher said
然後老師就說
Then I'm going to buy an electronic behavior gold like this
那我要去買個電子行為金這樣子
According to the price to be able to 5 million is too low
照價要能夠500萬太低了
But now it doesn't have to
不過現在其實也不必
Send it to a company to work with our company
就送到一家公司去跟我們合作的公司
They can help you quickly
他們就可以幫你很快的照
Just charge you two thousand yuan
只要收你兩千塊就可以
OK
OK
so what
所以呢
Because I actually play with this material
因為我其實玩這個材料
not for this
不是為這件事情的
I have been doing research on this material since 20...
我在做這個材料的研究已經從20...
that...
那個...
It should be said that in 2011
應該說2011年的時候
I will publish the first article
我就發表第一篇文章
i won't talk about that detail
我不談那個細節
The whole idea is this
那整個的想法是這樣
because we have a very accurate
就是因為我們有一個這非常精準的
This self-owned land gives us all the materials
這個自己商地給我們都材料
I just told him
那我剛剛跟他講說
That is to say, Jinwoyin should be placed very, very close
就是說要把金沃銀擺得非常非常近
Then how do I do this thing? I want to control it well.
那我怎麼做這件事情我要來控制得好
Then this approach becomes an interesting one.
那這個做法就變成有趣的一個做法
If you bring a girl, you will risk your life
如果拿一個女來那好好的冒著生命的危險
grind it very very flat
把它磨得非常非常平
Otherwise, female grinding flat is not a very soft girl
要不然女磨平不是一個女很軟
not a very
不是一個非常有
not a very safe thing to do
不是一個非常安全的事情
Because all the acids you need are explosive.
因為要的那些酸都是會爆炸的
Then let's treat it as this Yangji
那接著就把它做這個楊吉處理
Then it moves one by one like this
然後它就變成一個一個這樣動
Then I will use another acid to make this strong
接著我就再用一個酸把這個強弊
it likes to have a strong cons thickness
它自己喜歡有一個強弊的厚度
it decides by itself
都是它自己決定的
You just need to choose the voltage and it decides for itself.
你只要選那個電壓它就自己決定好了
This is completely under its own control
這個是完全是它自己控制的
As far as you have only one control, you choose the voltage
就你只有一個控制就是你選電壓
Then the distance between its movement and movement is determined by it
然後它之間動跟動之間的距離是它決定的
Then the size of its hole is also decided by it
然後它那個洞口大小也是它決定
Then you'll think
那做完了之後你就會想到
Then I have this tube because I already have it
那我因為已經有這個管子了
So the wall of this quad is too thin
所以這個四管的牆太薄
I can just open it up and corrode it
它我就可以把它打開就把它腐蝕一下
into another acid
放到一個另外一個酸裡面
And then when it's done it's
然後弄完了之後它就
then i become
那我就變成
This student from a master’s university did a thing that is the first time in the world to do everyone
這個碩士大學同學就做了一個全世界第一次做大家的事情
That is, I can fix the size of each silver particle
就是我可以把每一顆銀的顆粒的大小固定好
Then the distance between to adjust
然後之間的距離去調整
The point is that what we care about now is the diagonal seam between these two
重點是我們現在關心的是這兩顆之間的斜縫
The point between the two sets is not close enough
這兩顆之間的套得夠不夠近的這個點
We need to be able to accommodate it
我們要能夠去調供它
It does a series like this
它就做了一系列這樣
Then this is an electron that is clearly and imminently waiting
那這是一個電子顯而近在待的
The distance between is to five nanometers
之間的距離是到五奈米
Let me tell you about five nanometers. I have just shown it to you.
我跟大家講五奈米剛剛已經給大家看過
The rest of my atom group is three atoms or about five nanometers
我的其餘原子團就是三顆原子大概就是五奈米
Five nanometers means roughly the distance of fifteen atoms
五奈米的意思大概就是十五顆原子的距離
That is, we almost count the distance atom by atom
就是我們幾乎一顆一顆原子數過距離
Then the front of such a nanoparticle with a distance of five nanometers
那這個距離到五奈米的這樣一個奈米原粒子的正面
is a world record and is still a world record
是一個世界紀錄到現在還是世界紀錄
That's because of our approach
那因為我們這個做法
So it is easy to make very large area
所以很容易的做非常大的面積
I have brought my samples here
我有帶我樣品在這裡
Wait a minute and I'll open it up for everyone to see
等一下我會打開來給大家看
see you will feel like saying
看到你一定會覺得說
no habit
沒什麼習慣
doesn't look like anything
看起來就不像什麼東西
why spend so much time doing
為什麼要花這麼多時間去做
Then the particles it wins are placed like this
那它贏的顆粒就是這樣擺的
Put them here one by one
一顆一顆的擺在這個地方
then we'll go and see
那我們就去看
quickly
很快的
when we do it in a very delicate way
就是我們在做的很精緻的方式的時候
you can see
就可以看到
Win one by one and grow very, very well
一顆一顆贏就長得非常非常好
Then the distance between them is regulated very precisely.
然後之間的距離就調控得非常的精準
Then this one applied for a US patent in 2006
那這個在2006年申請美國專利
In 2008, he got the patent in the United States.
很快的2008年就拿到美國的專利
Such a wafer technology to make this nanosilver array
製作這個耐米銀陣列的這樣一個晶片技術
get a U.S. patent
就拿到美國的專利
Then in 2009 we put this technology
然後2009年我們就把這個技術
After one year, it will be transferred to a listed company in Taiwan
一年之後就計轉到台灣的一家上市公司
At that time, when Win was listed, it was called Hongkang.
那時候贏上市了就叫紅康
We bought this at Tech
我們在科技就買了這個
Just transfer our technology
就計轉了我們這個技術
Then I emphasize this thing here
然後這個東西我在這邊強調
It is not for studying bacteria
它不是為了研究細菌用
because i just told you
因為我剛剛跟你講說
what kind of molecule
什麼樣的分子
just put it on
只要放上去
i can hear it
我聽得到它聲音都可以
So this is a good place to do basic research
所以這是做一個基礎研究好的地方
Because basic research has a far-reaching impact
因為基礎研究它的影響是很深遠的
So it can be used to listen to bacteria
所以可以拿來聽細菌
A lot of people want you too why don't you
很多人也希望你為什麼不做
don't do virus
不做病毒
In fact, some people also use it as a virus
事實上有人也拿來做病毒
Then why don't you test the pollutants in the environment
那你為什麼不去測環境中的污染物
Pollutants in the atmosphere
大氣裡面的污染物
These things are molecules anyway
這些東西反正都是分子
I can even hear those molecules
我都可以聽那些分子的聲音
The availability of this detector
那這個偵測器的可用性
is very very profound
是非常非常深遠的
So Hongfang Technology is a material analyst
所以紅方科技他們是一個材料分析工
They figured this thing out
他們就計轉了這套東西
And now it is actually possible
然後目前事實上是已經可以
if someone is going to do it
如果有人要去做的時候
just do it
就可以去做
they can bring
他們可以拿來
Do this kind of service with everyone
跟大家做這樣的服務
but you have to ask first
但是你要先問說
Why spend so much money to listen
為什麼要花那麼多錢去聽
That's probably what a schematic looks like.
那這個一個示意圖大概就是這樣子
That is to say I have a win array
就是說我有一個贏的陣列
What about the winning array?
那這個贏的陣列呢
yes
是
The size and diameter of each won is about 25 years or so
每一顆贏的大小直徑大概25那一年左右
Then the distance between them here
然後他們之間的距離這邊
I want to express the hot zone
我又為了要表達熱區
this is the place
就是這個地方
really hot
真的是很熱
That's when the laser beam hits
就是那個雷射光打下來的時候
It spawns a common gun here
它在這邊產生一個共鎮槍
the so-called one
就是所謂的那個
The Service surface
那個Service表面
Plasma, no one can understand me when I say this
電漿子我講這個話其實沒有人聽得懂
surface plasmons
在表面電漿子
It's the electron over there that is hit by the laser light
就是那個電子在那邊被那個雷射光
Electrons in active emission are inside this silver
積極發射中的電子在這個銀裡面
A bunch of electrons start shaking each other
一堆電子就開始互相震起來
It's like a wave hit it and it vibrated
就像一股打它就震起來
The interaction effect
那這個互相交互的影響
so that the electron field in the region between them
使得他們之間的區域的電子場
become very strong
就變得非常的強
that looks like the overall effect
那看起來整體的效果
It's like it's very, very hot in that place
就好像那個地方非常非常的熱
So a molecule that is unfortunate enough to fall into it gets knocked pretty hard
所以一個不幸掉在這裡面的分子就被敲打得非常兇
So the sound it emits is very loud, and the signal you measure is very loud
所以它發出來的聲音就很大,你量到的信號就很大
The entire technology is in such a positive column that the function is in this place
這整個的技術就在這樣一個正列的功用就在這個地方
So we use this method to make the surface enhanced light source
所以我們就用這個方法去做表面增強光源
When you make a new technology, it has been 20 or 30 years longer than others
你做出來一個新的科技,然後已經是比別人玩做了二、三十年了
Compare it with the traditional method
你做出來跟傳統的方法比比比
So what's the traditional way?
所以傳統的方法是什麼?
or you take the silver and mess it up and make it rough
要不然你就把銀拿來弄亂亂的,把它弄粗粗的
Etch it with various amounts of acid, or which piece of glass you make
用各式量的酸去腐蝕它,或是你做哪一片玻璃
It's got some silver, let's just put some silver on it
它度一些銀,我們就拿一個度一些銀度在這上面
That's the traditional signal two
那這是傳統的信號兩道
It is mediocre, only here seems to have a little special frequency
就是平平平的,只有這邊看到好像有一點點特別的頻率
then this is our signal
那這個就是我們的信號
very clear this
很清楚的這個
It is probably ten times better than his traditional ones and more than a hundred times stronger.
大概就是比他一般傳統的都好十倍百倍以上的強度
That's why many people ask, why do you have such a loud voice?
所以很多人都問說那你們這個聲音這麼大
Then everyone will measure everything
那就大家就很所有東西都拿來量一量
But there are still many complicated things that I can't talk about today.
不過事實還有很多複雜的地方我今天都沒有辦法講
always a very interesting development
總是這是一個非常有趣的發展
so that we can really do this so-called
使得我們真正可以去很有控制的去做這個所謂的
When the shooter uses this word, it means to shoot
射手當用這個字就是射
In order to save the surface enhanced spectrum
為了減省表面增強光譜
It's a long story to slow down the spectrum bottom plate
拉慢光譜底板都講起來很長
So I call it the shooter blade technique
所以我把它就叫做射手底板的技術
If you want to measure various molecules
如果去量各種不同分子
It can be measured quite well under different concentrations.
在不同濃度底下都可以量得相當的不錯
After doing this, we will start talking
做了這個東西我們就開始說
What the hell do we have that thinks so is the amplifier
我們到底有一個這麼想的是放大器
such a sensitive amplifier
就這麼靈敏的放大器
If the method posted next to a certain house is called an amplifier
如果貼在某一家隔壁的方法就叫我們放大器
If you eavesdrop on the music in that POP next door
偷聽隔壁的那個POP裡面的音樂的話
It's too loud for me
聲音太大了對我沒什麼用
It's too low for me to hear
聲音太小了我就不一定聽得到
So I need to pick certain topics to listen to
所以我就需要去挑某一些主題來聽
It just so happened that the person we cooperated with was Professor Lin Qihong from Yangming University.
剛好我們合作的人是陽明大學的那個林齊宏教授
Professor Lin Qihong is currently the director of our Taipei City Health Bureau
林齊宏教授目前是我們台北市衛生局的局長
Director Lin said most of the time
那個林局長大部分的時間都說
You're doing a great job and we're here to do this for you.
你們做得不錯我們來合你做這樣子
Their interest is probably to study the various manifestations of hygienic creatures
他們的興趣大概就是研究衛生物的各式各樣的表現
Hygiene, everyone's first reaction is to say
衛生物大家第一個反應就是說
Hygienic can you know what he probably passed by so listen to his so-called voice
衛生物你能不能知道他大概經過這樣聽他的所謂的聲音
Does this know what kind of hygienic creature he is?
這有沒有了解他到底是什麼樣的衛生物
Or can you ask about when this hygienic product was poisoned?
或者是說你能不能夠問說這衛生物被下毒的時候
how did he react
他有什麼反應
So questions like this are what Professor Lin is more interested in.
所以諸如此類的問題就是林教授比較有興趣
Then of course we have many others
那我們當然還有很多其他的
Today I mainly talk about a large part of the cooperation with Professor Lin
今天我最主要講的就是主要跟林教授合作的一大部分
Then I will use a graphic to compare with you what you did before.
那我就再用圖像化的跟大家比說以前大家什麼做
In the past, everyone was an example of producing some nano-silver
以前大家就是產生一些奈米銀的例子
then grow some bacteria
然後就養一些細菌
Then put them together like a muddy one
然後就把他們獲成一個那個泥漿一樣獲在一起
Then measure a spectrum
然後就去量一個光譜
That's what he said
這就是他兩道的
Then he published an article
然後他就發表一篇文章
This was published in LNKM Water, a well-known chemical journal
這是發表在一個那個化學很好的雜誌 LNKM水裡面
and say that's the sound of germs
然後就說這就是細菌的聲音
tell him it's right
跟他說是對的
And then many years later when someone else does it
然後很多年之後又別人去做的時候
Both of them are like this
人家兩大都是這樣的
So everyone seems to be claiming that it's the sound of this bacterium
所以大家都好像有人宣稱是這種細菌的聲音
Someone said it was the sound of the bacteria
那有人說是那個細菌的聲音
because he is very, very much
因為他非常非常多
Why
為什麼
because he's just so hard to repeat
因為他就是很難重複
Because everyone's formula is different
因為每一個人的配方都不大一樣
then really in the end
然後真正到底
Because my straight man said he came from the voice of bacteria
因為我直男講說他是來自細菌的聲音
Then your bacteria live in a different environment
那你的細菌養在不同的環境裡面
he has different molecules
他有不同的分子
Then eat differently
然後吃的也不一樣
So even the same type of bacteria
所以即便是同類型的細菌
He may hear different voices
他可能聽到的聲音都不一樣
because he emits different molecules
因為他散發出不同的分子
So this repeatability is a big problem
所以這個重複性是一個很大的問題
Then it was more like
那後來做得比較好像
It's all fairly stable
這都已經算是相當穩定的
This is a beautiful result
這很漂亮的結果
this is a
這個是一個
This is a
這是一個
The spectrum of bacteria in our big factory
我們這大廠感菌的這個光譜
It's pretty similar to what we did the first time.
跟我們先次做的都蠻類似的
Bacteria like them
那他們那樣的細菌
Dachang bacteria
就是大廠感菌
you go and see
你去看
His screen also has some
他的螢幕也有一些
Silver particles are placed at the bottom
銀的粒子擺在底下
that same back
那同樣的背部
Look at his silver particles like this
你去看他的銀的粒子是這樣子
Just put them one by one like this
就一顆一顆擺這樣
That's under the exact same index
那在一模一樣的指數之下
Our silver array looks like this
我們那個銀的陣列是這樣
make it bigger
那把它放大起來
Look at each one like a pebble
看就是每一顆就像一個鵝卵石的
Then every time I think about it myself,
那我自己常常每次想到這件事情的時候
my reaction to that germ
對那細菌我的反應
that's how it feels
也是這樣的感覺
That is to say, it is like being in the sun
就是說這像像是大太陽底下
Then we find some frogmen
然後我們找一些蛙人
and drop it on this pebble beach
然後把它丟到這個鵝卵石的沙灘上面
like the troop on super ice
就像部隊在超冰一樣的
and make them feel
然後讓他們覺得
Then do the hard work over there every day
然後在那邊每天做很辛苦的那個
various
各式各樣的
make a move over there
在那邊做個動作
And then the sound they give off goes like this
然後他們散發出來的聲音這樣
The way we did it before is that
那我們以前的做的方式就是那個
The pebbles on the beach are messy
沙灘的鵝卵石就是很亂
then everywhere
然後到處都是
then we are very very even
那我們是非常非常均勻
still very very good
還得非常非常好
Well, if you want to go down carefully and talk about this
那如果大家仔細要下去看說這個
What does the whole image look like
整個圖像大概像什麼樣
that is
就是說
I spread the bacteria on such a
我又把細菌鋪在這樣一個
win array above
贏的陣列上面
That's probably the bacteria
那細菌細菌大概是這樣
Underneath each bacterium is actually
那每一顆細菌底下其實
Paved
鋪了
This servo map doesn't have that much muscle
這個伺服圖沒有那麼筋骨
Under every bacterium
那每一顆細菌底下
From our scale
從我們的尺度來看
Under each bacterium is paved
每一顆細菌底下是鋪了
An example of one or two thousand winnings
一兩千顆的贏的例子
under a bacterium
一隻細菌底下
because of that
因為那個
The sawfish between that sawfish is
那個鋸魚之間的鋸魚是
around 30nm
30奈米左右
It's between the sawfish and the sawfish
就是那個鋸魚和鋸魚之間
Sawfish 30
鋸魚30
Of course the bacteria looks like a microphone
那細菌菌當然是一麥克風的樣子
So it's 30 times 30
所以就是要用30乘30
There are a lot of examples out there
就鋪了很多的例子在那裡
There is a light in there
那裡面有光一隻
This is the shell of a cleanser bacteria
這是一個潔面圖細菌的菌殼
Each piece is drawn according to size on this picture
每一件是這圖上面都按尺寸畫
This is 25nm, this is 5nm
這個是25奈米,這個是5奈米
Bacterial shells probably use these to stand
細菌的菌殼大概用這些來站
Probably a sentence of 7 or 80 nanometers
大概可能是7、80奈米的一句
That light will penetrate the whole bacteria
那光線是會穿透整支細菌的
So this blue part is talking about the inside of the bacteria
所以這個藍色的部分講的是細菌的內部
So if you draw according to this rhythm
所以如果按照這個曲律畫的話
The real bacteria is about the size of the roof
真正的細菌大小大概就是在屋頂上面
live so big
居那麼大一支
It's such a big thing that the color light shoots in
就是那麼大一個東西到蕾色光射進來
then the distance
然後就距離
Bacteria no matter what it emits
細菌不管是它散發出來的
Or the signal on the wall that is about 10 nanometers nearby
或是它牆上貼在附近大概10奈米左右的信號
the sound of those molecules
那些分子發出來的聲音
we can all hear
我們都有可能聽得到
So I just gave you
所以我剛給大家
Let me show you those spectra
放給大家看的那些光譜
It's actually a big chorus
其實是一個大合唱
It's a lot of molecules together
就是很多分子大家一起
the overall effect is taking place
都在發生整體的效果
Not just one bacterium
並不是只有一支細菌
is a bacterium
是一支細菌
exudes a lot
散發出很多
many molecules those molecules have in common
很多的分子 那些分子共同
A shimmer of vibration
震盪出來的一個光澤
Bacteria can explain to you a little bit here
細菌在這邊可以跟大家稍微解
Basically, there are two classes
大致上就是有兩個類
It is the Yangshi bacteria in Ge'an City and the Yinshi bacteria in Ge'an City
就是隔安市陽市菌跟隔安市陰市菌
The whole category is roughly like this
那個整個分類大概是這樣的
Then they wait a minute and I will tell everyone to see him
那他們等一下我會跟大家看他說
Anshi Yangshi Bacteria
隔安市陽市菌
He has a typical scrambling voice
他滿典型的拼盪聲音
When there are molecules under these
這些底下這邊都有分子的時候
He has a very, very loud voice
那跟他有一個聲音特別特別大
is 733
就是733
Guo Shu
郭樹
Wait a minute and I'll explain this to you 733
等一下我會跟你解釋這個733
Just what you want to say about 733 times
就大家想說大概733次的意思
But this time we have to multiply by
但是這個次還要再乘以
Three times ten to the tenth power like this
三乘以十的十次方這樣
Another kind of example
那另外一類的比方說
Anshi Yinshi Bacteria
這隔安市陰市菌
Everyone is most familiar with Escherichia coli
大家最熟的就是大腸感菌
That's what everyone often hears about bacteria in Yangshi, Anshi.
那隔安市陽市菌大家也滿常聽到的就是
Botrytis aureus
金黃色葡萄酒菌
This is one of these two types of bacteria
這就是一個這兩類的菌
Then there is this category
那還有這一類
Molecular infection
這是說分子染菌
Molecular infectious bacteria look like tigers
分子染菌大觀虎看起來就跟別人
It has co-existed with us humans for thousands of years
跟我們人類是幾乎是共存了幾千年的時間
Mycobacterium fidgetii
一個就是費捷合的分支感菌
Mycobacteria
大家都知道費捷合的分支感菌
Mycobacterium Naficella is a very, very tough home
那費捷合的分支感菌是一個非常非常難纏的家
it can hide inside your body
它可以躲在你身體裡面
Then never get sick
然後一輩子都不發病
wait until you're older
等到你年紀大的時候
it just started to trouble you
它才開始找你麻煩
Another branch of mycobacterium is let us
另外一支分支感菌是讓我們
Everyone has a lot of text settings
大家很多文字設定了
that's where we are
就是我們在那邊
we are over there
我們在那邊
Many texts are set to be leprosy
很多文字設定了就是麻風病
Leprosy is also a type of mycobacterium
麻風病也是分支感菌的一種
those two
那這兩種
What about this type of infection?
這一類型的感菌呢
Mycobacterium
都是分支感菌
Its spectrum is like everything else
它的光譜跟其他的東西都有
big difference
滿大的不同
just the same
就是大同小異
let's wait
那我們等一下
I will probably let everyone listen to this voice
我大概就會讓大家聽聽這個聲音
how did it play
到底是怎麼播的
Then I'm going to
那接下來我要把
heard about it
聽到這件事情
not really us
不是真正我們
I just heard that go to the room
就是聽到去間別
not really our biggest concern
並不是我們真正最關心的問題
What we are actually more concerned with is that
我們其實比較關心的是說
How did Xixun react when we poisoned him?
細訊被我們下毒的時候他到底怎麼反應
because why
因為為什麼
Because if you're going to talk to someone who does medicine
因為如果你要跟做醫學的人談
For example, when we talked with the doctor of National Taiwan University
比方說我們跟台大醫生談的時候
They said you should not tell me which strain it is so detailed
他們就說你不要跟我講是哪一種菌種那麼細緻
Because I only have three medicines
因為我只有三種藥而已
One is isolated positive bacteria
一種就是隔安式陽式菌
One is specialized in medical isolation type negative bacteria
一種就是專門醫隔安式陰致菌的
Then the other one is the plum fungus
然後另外一種就是梅菌
Just tell me these three
你就跟我講這三種
Anyway, I only have these three options for medication.
反正我用藥只有這三個選擇而已
you won't tell me too much about medicine
你不會跟我講太多藥
Just tell me these three
就告訴我這三種就好了
Then I started taking drugs
然後我就開始下藥了
if you don't tell me
那如果你不跟我講的話
Then I will download all three
那我就三種都下
Then when the time comes, let’s talk about the abuse of antibiotics anyway.
然後到時候再把反正那個抗生素濫用這件事情
It's because the upper management told me not to use it.
是叫歌述上面叫我不要用
But from the patient's point of view
可是從病人的角度來看
our family is dying
我們家人都快死了
Of course you just drop all the atomic bombs and everything
你當然就是所有的原子彈什麼東西都全部丟下去
And then it looks like there's something going on
然後看起來那種有起死
When you are about to die, there will be one less and one less
快沒死的時候就少一種少一種
see if he survives
看他還活得下來
you usually look like this
你通常都是這樣子
So antibiotics say no to abuse
所以抗生素說不濫用這件事情
It's actually very difficult
其實是很困難的
that sentence i said
我講的那個句話
I didn't say it, but they took it and tied it all down
不是我講的,結果他們就拿來就全部都扎下去
This is what Mr. Ke Wenzhe told me
這是柯文哲先生跟我講
Because Mr. Ke Wenzhe is the boss of a Korean doctor in our cooperative team
因為柯文哲先生是我們合作團隊的一位韓醫士的老闆
As far as the medicines probably cost money, there are probably four types of medicines
藥大概出錢的了解,大概有四大類的藥
The first way to think of attacking others is probably
第一種想到攻擊別人的方法,大概就是
The hardest, and easiest-to-shake method
最辛苦的,而且最容易抖手方法
Just when the family is splitting
就是當趁人家在分裂的時候
to attack, that is to say
發動攻擊,那就是說
Being careful doesn't mean growing up, his shell always grows up
細心不是要長大,他殼總要長大
So I figured out a way to stop him from growing out of the shell
所以我就想辦法把他長大的殼的地方阻止他
Or break his shell, because he wants to grow
或是把他殼弄破的話,因為他要長
That doesn't end up growing, there's always a weakness
那個不是終於要生長,總會有弱點
If you cut him off at that time, he will list the information
就在那個時候把他截斷的話,他就列料
It's a kind of shell that's attacking his cells
這是一種,就是攻擊他的細胞的表殼
The other is the synthesis of proteins that go in and attack his cells
另外一種就是進去攻擊他細胞的蛋白質的合成
Don't let his protein cells
不要讓他蛋白質的那細胞
probably won't last
大概也長不下去
The third way is to directly turn the entire outer shell of the cell into a
第三種就是直接就把細胞的表殼整個把它變
This is also the fourth
這也是以第四種
The fourth is the process of how to make the DNA in it
第四種就是它裡面的DNA要怎麼去做的這個過程當中
let's keep fucking it
我們繼續把它亂搞
then fix it
然後弄整它
it won't survive or grow
它就活不下去或是不會長大
A germ can't kill you
一隻細菌是殺不了你
Would you be a million short
你會不會差一百萬
A bacterium will not
一隻細菌是不會
you are afraid of it
你怕它
You have no reason to be afraid of cockroaches
你怕髒狼沒什麼道理
But you're right to be afraid of germs
但是你怕細菌是有道理的
Because if the bacteria arrive
因為細菌如果到就是
copy two two two two every half hour
每半個鐘頭就複製兩隻兩隻兩隻
At the time of the twenty-fourth square, it will soon take up the reputation of this body
二的二十四方的時候很快就占美名這個身體了
Therefore, it is only needed when the calamity is small
所以真正小到磨災小的時候才需要
Ant, you don't need to be too nervous
螞蟻你還不需要太緊張
But when you start to lose sight you just get nervous
但是開始看不見的時候你就是要緊張了
By the time I can't see it, it's already thinner than your hair
開始看不見的時候就已經進到比你的頭髮還細
Your hair is about 100 micrometer
你的頭髮大概是100 micrometer左右
The bacteria I'm talking about is your hair and cut it into a hundred pieces
那我在講的細菌就是你的頭髮再把它切成一百片
into a million
分成一百個萬
one hundred
一百條
One Hundred Feet Zun
一百尺尊
We're probably just starting to say yes, then we'll read on.
我們大概就是開始說好那我們就來下讀
We read it from bacteria
從細菌講出來就被我們下讀
You can see the result of the next reading, that is to say
下讀的結果大家就看到就是說
I have written about the birth and death of bacteria after we read it
我都寫了細菌被我們下讀以後的產教生
So it was a joy to start him reading Bacteria
所以開始把他下讀細菌本來就是很快樂的
Like a whale in the bottom of the sea singing his own favorite song
就像海底的鯨魚唱的他自己喜歡唱的歌
Just the same spectrum doesn't change
就同樣的光譜都沒有改變
just keep walking
就一直走走
At 50 minutes, he suddenly knew and said wow
走到50分鐘的時候他突然知道說哇
He's already been attacked.
改機打掉了他已經被攻擊了
So his entire spectrum has completely changed.
所以他整個光譜都已經完全變了
then to the last
接著到最後這個
After waiting for a while, he answered the spectrum again
等到一段時間之後他又回答這個光譜
I won't talk about that detail today
那今天我不講那個細節
In fact, we've had a lot of work on this spectrum lately.
其實是我們最近已經有很多對這個光譜
What exactly does that mean
到底是什麼意思
we have a deeper understanding
我們有一更深入的了解
But today we don't like him
不過今天我們都不喜歡他
Remember these numbers the point is to say
記住這些數字重點是說
about a pinhead
大概一個針頭左右的時候
Bacteria already feel his pain
細菌就已經感受到他的痛苦
Then start teaching
然後就開始殘教
Then we'll give all kinds of medicine
那我們就下各種不同的藥
Teacher Lin Xuhong and his laboratory
林徐鴻老師他們實驗室
There are various
有各種不同的
All kinds of poisonous hands, they all have a way to do this
各種不同的毒手他們都有辦法下這樣子
So what they do is
所以他們下的就是
If you're off the drug, you'll be fine listening to him all the time.
如果你沒下藥那就一直聽他都沒事
There are such drugs as
有這一類的藥就是
Drugs of this class that grow on the epidermis of the main segment bacteria
主段細菌表皮生長的這一類的藥
That's 55 minutes 45 minutes
這跟講是55分鐘 45分鐘
about an hour or so
大概一個鐘頭左右
They bacteria start to give birth
他們細菌就開始產交
His so-called procreation means
他的所謂產交的意思就是
There is a huge change in Optics Valley
光谷就有一個巨大的變化
It's that voice that sounds sudden
就是那個聲音聽起來突然
You thought you were listening to the cello
本來你以為聽的是大提琴
suddenly became sona
突然一下子變成索納
or something
或什麼之類的
what it sounds like happened
聽起來就怎麼發生什麼事的
so
這樣
The other category is to
另外那一類是去
During protein synthesis in the main segment bacteria
主段細菌內部蛋白質合成的時候
sounds reasonable
聽起來就蠻道理
quite reasonable
蠻有道理的
idiom like flame
好像炎之成語
After waiting for half a day
等了半天之後
12 hours later
12個鐘頭之後
Bacteria finally suffocated
細菌終於才憋住了
hold for half an hour
憋了半個鐘頭
After half a day, I finally couldn't take it anymore
半天之後終於受不了了
started giving birth
就開始產交了
this is very interesting
這個很有趣的
see this time
就看到這個時間
Actually for this matter
其實對於這件事
Especially an instant detection response of wanting to heal or something
特別是想要治療或什麼的一種即時的偵測反應
may be useful
都可能有用
they are
他們對這些事情是
Such a method fast one
這樣一個方法快速的一個
detection
偵測
Then directly observe in the monitor
然後在monitor就直接在直接觀測
Such an instant response technology
這樣一個即時的反應的科技
they are interested
他們是有興趣
Then we sat there and wanted to say
接著就是說我們坐到那個地方就想說
what are we going to do next
我們接下來要做什麼
Already talked to him and it sounds like it might work.
已經跟他講說好像聽起來這個快有用
The next step, of course, is to be the station master.
接下來當然就是要上站長
Just say yes, or you can catch a few bacteria to really catch them all.
就說好不然你們就去抓幾隻細菌來真的抓都看
what bacteria to catch
要抓什麼細菌
The first one is that of course we will go to school to catch
第一個就是說那我們當然就到學裡面抓
why
為什麼呢
Our real science should not have bacteria in it
我們真正的學裡面不應該有細菌
If there are bacteria, it is called
如果有細菌的時候就叫做
Bacteriology certificate or university certificate
菌學證或是大學證
when you catch bacteria
抓到細菌的時候就
it will be painful
會蠻痛苦
That
那
These
這些
It's about time. I can, maybe, tell a few jokes.
時間還差不多我可以應該可以講幾個笑話
that is
就是
That's because when I started doing it, I started going around
那因為開始做那時候我就開始到處
ask and report
去求也也告來
We're going to send the machine to National Taiwan University Hospital
我們要把機器送進台大醫院
That's when I started to know
那這時候我才開始知道
What is played in the Japanese contact drama is called the white drama tower
日本聯繫劇裡面演的什麼叫做白色劇塔
in this way
這樣子
That's the one
就是那個
No matter how you say it, you have to go over there and bet on a small place.
怎麼講都要去那邊押一塊小地方說
The machine will be given to you and then what?
機器送給你 然後呢
Send an assistant to help you with the experiment
派助理來幫你做實驗
you don't spend a dime
你一毛錢都不要花
you just let us come here with you
你只要讓我們來這邊陪你們
Then I will report the result to you after finishing
然後做完還跟你報告結果
Why don't you go in?
還是不用進去 怎麼講呢
Later, I had no choice but to find Dean Yang at that time.
後來我只好去找那時候的楊院長
Yang half time
有楊半時
Yang Banshi worked very hard to help us explain
楊半時就去很努力的去幫我們講
Then one day I met Principal Li at that time
然後有一天遇到那時候的李校長
Principal Li Sicheng
李四成李校長
Principal Li told me about this
李校長就跟我講說這個
Yang Banshi
楊半時
Yang Banshima is not enough to legislate
楊半時馬還不夠立法
I should be more capable
我應該是比較有辦法的
National Taiwan University this
台大這個
only two are fourteen
只有兩個人是十四職等
one is medicine
一個就是醫學
hospital director
醫院的院長
The other is the principal
另外一個就是校長
so there should be a way
所以應該有辦法
After he finished speaking, there was an interval of five minutes
然後講完他就隔了五分鐘
he wants to say
有他想說
I think I probably can't do this
我看我大概也沒辦法這樣子
What do you call a white lens?
怎麼叫白色的鏡頭
Then Mr. Yang is very busy
然後來楊議員長很大忙
Then go talk to the dean of the medical school
然後就去跟醫學院的院長
Talk to the director of the hospital
跟醫院的院長講講
We are finally in the department in the important town
我們終於在重鎮那個科裡面
just find a place
就找到一個地方
a very small corner
一個非常小的角落
Then you can help others to do experiments there
然後就可以在那裡幫人家做實驗
It's totally free
就是完全免費振振
to help people do experiments
去幫人家做實驗
It's so hard to do this thing
就這麼樣的辛苦在做這件事情
Because it's from the Congress
因為這是國特會的
Nanostate project
奈米國家案計畫
So they want us to have some industrial applications
所以他們希望我們有一些產業的應用
So I personally spent a lot of effort
所以我個人是花了很多的心血
then do this
那要做這件事情
Of course the first thing is fine
當然第一件事情就好
Then you're going to catch bacteria
那你要去抓細菌
like say
就像說
Yang's bacteria are
楊的細菌就是
That is the feeding machine
那個就是飼養的飼料機
If you really want to catch bacteria
那如果要真的抓細菌
Then go grab and release the flasher
那就要去抓放閃機
That's when we caught the machine first
我們是那時候先把機抓到
otherwise how did you come
不然的話你怎麼來
Is it necessary to find a way to catch it?
那是不是就要想辦法去抓
Then we later had a professor
那我們後來就有一個教授
this is the one
這就是那個
He was my blogging researcher at the time
那時候他是我的博社研究員
Professor Liu Dinghong
叫劉定宏的教授
Now at the Department of Materials Science at National Taiwan University
現在在台灣大學的那個材料科學系
He proposed a method at that time
他就當時他就提出了一個方法
Just count all these things
就是把這些萬物沒數
Du on the array surface we win
杜在我們贏的陣列表面上
Wangu Homestay itself is a medicine
萬古民宿本身是個藥
It's actually a tool next to the connection of the protein
它其實是旁跟蛋白質的連結的一個工具
Wangu Homestay is a medicine
萬古民宿是一個藥
this thing is interesting
這件事情是有趣的
Why does medicine help you catch bacteria
藥為什麼會幫你抓細菌
This thing is intuitive
這件事情很直覺想起來是
It's funny looking back now
現在回想起來是非常有趣
But it was just a sense of fact
可是當時只是說事實感
It turned out really well.
結果事出來結果真的蠻好
like here is to say
像這邊是覺得說
It's just a little lower on top of my floor
在我的底板上面就低了一低
The place of Wangu B&B is just a little low
萬古民宿的地方就一小低
Then this little low size
然後這一小低的大小
This one is only about ten or fifteen microns.
這個只有大概十幾十五micron左右
a small area
一個小小區域
Where there is a low place, the bacteria will be in the water
有低的地方就把細菌在水裡面
Then just shake it and wait
然後就把它抖一抖等
wait ten or twenty minutes later
等十二十分鐘以後
found that bacteria only stick to this
發現細菌都只有黏在這上面
I caught the bacteria
我就把細菌抓了
like say put some in there and run countdown
就像說把一些放進去倒數跑
Or in fact, it is more like the previous Margin Camp
或者是說其實比較像以前的補倉營的
that warehouse paper
那個倉營紙
Just put a meal here
就擺一張餐就擺在這裡
Then
然後
When I come back from get off work, I will watch it for three and a half years
我下班回來的時候去看個三年半年
Everyone will feel that this
大家都會覺得 其實這個
Think of medicine as a catch thing
把藥當作一個捕捉這件事情
Then it can be used to measure the tiger
然後又能夠拿來測光虎這件事情
This is a semi-accidental discovery
這個是一個半意外的發現
This result quickly attracted the attention of many people.
這個成果很快的就引起很多人的注意
actually looking back
其實回首去講
I just said that when building this thing
我剛說過建立這件事情的時候
Actually, I have a logic in my heart
其實我心裡是有一個邏輯的
The logic is this is to say
那個邏輯是這樣就是說
why the medicine works
藥為什麼有效
In fact, we have used the medicine for a long time with great motivation.
其實藥我們用了很久很大本動
don't even know why it works
都不知道它為什麼有效
In fact, we are still looking for the philosophy of medicine
其實我們到現在都尋找藥的哲學
There is actually no difference between the license plate of the mayor of Shenlong
跟神龍市長牌照其實沒有差別
We are not much stronger than Shenlong City
我們並沒有比神龍市厲害很多
We just agreed on what kind of molecule I would synthesize.
我們就是說好我合成一個什麼樣分子
Then I'll try it out
然後我就拿來試試看
If it is effective or not, it will continue to moisten every day if it is effective or not
有效沒效就每天都在有效沒效一直潤
that's the whole thing
這就是整個就是這樣子
like vancomyle knows it works
像萬古梅樹知道它有效
it's been a long time
已經很久很久
But how to kill the bacteria
可是到底怎麼把那個細菌殺掉
this matter to this day
這件事情到今天
It is not very clear that
也並不是有非常清楚的這樣
because that mechanism is a hard problem
因為那個機制是一個很難的問題
But effective energy is a test method that can be used to do
但是有效能下是一個用檢驗方法可以拿來做的
Wangu plum tree has been known for thirty or forty years
萬古梅樹已經知道三四十年了
I was thinking about my opinion on the matter
我當時在想這件事情的看法
It's four steps
這已經四步了
If the everlasting plum tree enters your studies
萬古梅樹如果進到你的學業裡面去
cells everywhere
到處跟牆地上的細胞
Or if the classmates stick together
或者是同學什麼都黏在一起的話
Then you must be carrying a lot of weight
那你一定負重一大堆
Then you are already dead, right?
那你人早就死了對不對
then he must have a way
那他一定是有個辦法
It's like the key and lock method
就是像鑰匙跟鎖流的辦法
he goes to find something he likes sticky
他去找到他喜歡黏的東西
Then if he is effective against bacteria
那他如果對細菌有效
He should be with him at least like to be close together
他應該跟他至少會喜歡靠在一起
Under such a concept
那這樣的一個概念底下
we just do some searching
我們就做一些尋找
The everlasting plum tree happens to be here half a year at this corner
那萬古梅樹剛好是在這裡半年的這角
But recently we've made some very subtle discoveries
不過最近我們有一些非常細膩的發現
How on earth did the plum tree accumulate and develop this bacteria sticking in it?
到底萬古梅樹怎麼積發這個細菌黏在這裡面
Actually there is a very interesting story
其實是有一個非常有趣的故事
Then I hope after a year
那我希望在一年之後
I can tell you a better story
可以跟大家講一個更精彩的故事
As a result, the result of the measurement is like this, that is, when you took ten thousand shares of plum trees and pasted them
結果去量的結果是這樣,就是你拿了萬股梅樹貼上去的時候
Where the amount of bacteria is not added to the plum tree, the red snowball prefers to stick to it
量到的細菌沒有加萬股梅樹的地方,紅雪球比較喜歡沾在上面
The place where the plum tree is added is that the bacteria prefer to stick to it
加了萬股梅樹的地方,就是細菌比較喜歡沾在上面
Just when you're elected, it makes some sense to our intuition
就當你選出來,這跟我們的直覺想起來也有點道理
If Wangu Meishu likes to stick to your red snowball when it goes in, then something is probably wrong with you
如果萬股梅樹進去就喜歡黏到你的紅雪球的話,那你大概就出事了
If you take one injection, you will die first, and the bacteria will not be there, because it can't find the bacteria
你打一針打下去,你先死掉,細菌都還沒,因為它沒找不到細菌
Then go to your student's side and beat around, and then let the red snowball go on it
然後就到你學員那邊亂打,然後就能讓紅雪球在上面去
so this whole afternoon looks like fun
所以這整個下午看起來是有趣的
Then it turns out that the relationship between time, I think I must find some time
然後結果時間的關係,我就看起來我一定要找到留點時間
Then broadcast the sound of bacteria for you to click off, otherwise there must be members
然後播細菌的聲音給你們點掉,不然都要有會員
As a result, of course we spent a lot, the team is very big
結果我們當然有花很多,這團隊是非常大的
Spend a lot of time researching and saying, if we really want to be useful
花很多時間去研究說,那我們真的如果要有用的話
How to improve the settings of the instrument
要怎麼樣儀器的設定要怎麼改進
What our lab is doing is probably, all the labs use such equipment
我們實驗室在做的大概就是,實驗室用的都是這樣的設備
that is
就是
The equipment used in the lab is phantom active
實驗室裡面用的設備是幻象積極的
equipment is expensive
設備是貴的不得了
It was the Zhuangren circle who gave it to me
就是那個莊人圈給我
i will give my experience
我會給我的經過
brought it and bought the machine
拿來然後就買了機器
To the team I work with at Yangming University
送給陽明大學我合作的團隊
The way I work with him is to say who and which team member needs
我跟他合作的方式就是說誰哪一個團隊的成員需要
give him the machine
把機器送給他
Then write a letter to laugh with them
然後還要寫個信跟他們笑
I told him about the machine I'm giving to your co-op team
我跟他講說我要送給你們合作團隊的機器
then can you give him a space
然後你可不可以給他一個空間
After asking for half a day
求了半天之後
finally reached
終於達到
Do you have a hard time giving you a small room
你有沒有其難給你一個小房間
you send that phantom machine
你把那個幻象機送來
Then we sent a
然後我們就送了一台
until now put
到現在就放在
So it's really good to work with me
所以跟我合作實在是不錯的
that machine
那個機器
very very strict
非常非常嚴格的精
Many things are very elf
很多的東西都是非常精靈
I just saw that most of the materials are made from such machines
剛剛看到那大部分的資料都是從這樣的機器做
but you have to put
可是你要放到
You can't put a phantom machine in the hospital
醫院裡面去你不能放幻象機
that phantom machine is too big
那幻象機太大了
That big hospital every time
那台大醫院每一個時間
There's only one piece of each and it's that big
每一件都只有一件,就這麼大
Put hundreds of cameras in
把換相機那麼百個百的進去
So start my co-op partner
所以就開始我的合作的夥伴
the long-term cooperation
那個長期合作的
It is Wang Jingqiao from the Tie Center of National Taiwan University driving the car
就是台大領帶中心的王靖橋駕車
At once
就
designed to make the whole thing very, very small
設計的把整個事情弄得非常非常縮小
a microscope, then a spectrum
一個顯微鏡,然後光譜
or something, take it all
什麼的,全部拿來整個
It's a bit table-oriented
就是有點桌向型的
Then we also put a machine in the Central Administration Bureau of Taiwan
然後我們也放了一台機器到台灣的集管局
because of careful research
因為做細心的研究
May be to P2 Level
可能是要到P2 Level
Mainly what we do over there is mycobacteria
主要是我們在那邊做的就是分支桿菌的
that machine
那那個機器
When students go in, you all operate N95
學生進去你們操作都是N95
I go in every day and do experiments like that
每天進去在做那樣的實驗
that was a very, very hard experiment
那非常非常辛苦的實驗
that requires very little space
那需要的就是很小的空間
and then inside the life safety cabinet
然後要在生命安全櫃裡面
So there are actually a lot of sad stories in it.
所以這其實裡面有很多很心酸的故事
I don't talk about time today.
今天時間關係我也不講
that if
那如果
If you stand down, just say yes, if you may want to be in
站下去的話,就說好那如果你可能要在
really smaller space
真的更小的空間裡面
then you are the one
那你就那個
The machine doesn't need to be so good, then you can make something like a desktop
機器不需要那麼好,那你就做一個像是桌上型的東西
So put the whole design to say
所以就把整個設計到說
My wafer is the one that can put the wafer
我的晶片就是可以把晶片放
That chip is for biologists to get used to
那個晶片為了讓生物學家習慣
So our chip is basically made in
所以我們那個晶片就根本就把它做在
Just make it what everyone is used to
根本就把它做在大家習慣的那個
It's the Bone Noodle House
就是白骨面房
This is it
就是這個
this product
就是這個生產物
look
看
It's like a pixel
就是有像素的感覺
if you speak directly
如果直接就講說
this is above
這就是上面
yours
你一顆的
You don't take it, you keep hitting it
你這個不帶你一直打在上面
a little bit of what you see above
上面看到的一點點
so just a little click
所以就稍微的按一下
Simple and feels like the upper half
簡單的有像上半層的感覺
is your button
就是你的按鍵
that's it
就是這樣子
relatively stable
比較安定嘛
That's dense enough
這樣就夠密滿了
then one by one
然後一顆一顆
what does your fingerprint sound like
你的指紋是什麼樣的聲音
right
對
Then it becomes very
那這樣的話就變得很
for the entire process
就整個製程
or give us the possibility to generate very quickly
或是讓我們有可能很快速的產生
many such detectors
很多這樣的偵測器
You think of it as an amplifier
你把它想成就是放大機
and then you stick it on something
然後你貼在什麼東西上
you have the opportunity to hear the molecular voice
你就可以有機會去聽到分子的聲音
Do you want to listen to basic training?
是不是要聽基訓
Because we found a partner who happened to be doing basic training
因為我們找到合作的剛好是做基訓
If anyone here would like to hear other
如果在座有人喜歡聽別的
Or like to eavesdrop on what other people are saying
或是喜歡偷聽別人講話的話
don't care
那就立場別論
Then of course I still have the answer to my dream
那當然我還有回應夢想
Because I just said that those are small ones.
因為我剛剛講那些就是小的就得了
Jihun is 1 million smaller than us
基訓是比我們小100萬
1 million times
100萬倍的
why so big
為什麼要那麼大
It's a big deal for Kihun
對基訓來講是很大的事
big to the first step
很大到第一步
unbelievable is
不可思議的就是
People are weak
人氣力不及
less popular
人氣不及
to do
要做的
if the real future
如果真正未來
if to do
如果要做的
make it such a big one
把它做成這麼大的一個
hand in hand
手拿在手上
So this is pretending to be a photo
所以這個就裝成一張照片
Then we follow this photo
然後我們就跟上這個照片
and then like this
然後這樣子就
just not the same
就是並不一樣
Separated things should then still
分離的東西然後應該還會
Just put it on the back of this photo
就放到背面這個照片
is twitter
就是推特
That's my bacteria from last night
就是我昨天晚上我的細菌
what song did you sing to me like this
跟我唱了什麼歌這樣
that's a good idea too
那也是有不錯的想法
so
所以
The technology of miniaturization is not a
微小化這個科技並不是一個
real problem
真正的問題
The problem is in the self-preparation of the sample
問題是在樣品的自備
Get the samples and prepare yourself
拿到樣品自備就是
I managed to get into National Taiwan University Hospital this year
我這一年來好不容易爬進台大醫院
What you do in pain every day
裡面每天在痛苦做的事
those things are not my specialty
那些事情都不是我的專長
It turns out that those are the expertise of life scientists
原來那些都是生命科學家的專長
How many molecules are there in that
那學裡面有多少分子
There are many, many molecules in a drop of blood
一滴血裡面有很多很多的分子
those molecules in the end
那些分子到底
meaning that he may be in
意思就是他有可能在
At least find a child, right?
至少找孩子對不對
Then you'd be making a fuss
那你就等於鬧轟轟的
then how on earth do you listen to him
那你到底怎麼去聽他
Why did you stop him from happening first?
你怎麼先把不准他發生的
Then hand it over and get rid of it first
那就交先幹掉
why this whole bunch of things
為什麼是這整個一大堆的事情
It was when you were experimenting
就是以前你在做實驗的時候
very simple
都很簡單
I'm so happy when I'm writing a thesis
寫論文的時候也很高興這樣子
Then when the reporter was waiting for the meeting
然後那個開記者在待會的時候
nor
也沒有
Very happy, not very happy, but my collaborators are very happy
蠻高興的,不是很高興,是我的合作者都很高興
There are three minutes left, let's listen to the sound
剩下三分鐘的時間,我們就來聽一聽聲音
If this speaker does not broadcast sound, please donate a little more money when you go out, and you will finally be like this
如果這個音響沒有播出聲音的話,請大家出去的時候多捐一點錢,你終於就這樣
This is Mr. Dachangan, what you have measured is such a light map
這就是大產感君,量到的就是這樣一個光圖
I will play this main one, according to this size, the 10 most important and louder sounds, I will start playing according to the loudest sound
我會播這個主要,按照這個大小,10個最主要的比較大聲的音,我會按照最大的聲音開始播
The background sound gets rid of it first, that's the kind of background
背景的聲音先把它除掉,就是那種背景
The ten sound waves I picked, I have a lot of waves, I can also make all ten sounds cooperate
我挑的十個音波,我好多種波吧,我也可以叫十個音都合作
At the beginning, did anyone recognize the 700-odd sound?
那剛一開始那個,那個七百多的音有人聽出來嗎?
Can anyone tell me that it is really a positive frequency of 720 or so
有誰可以跟我講,那個真的就是正頻率就是七百二十幾
Then this is mycobacteria, so let's remove the background
那這個是分支桿菌的,一樣我們把背景除掉
Louder, louder, louder, louder
音量比較高,音量比較高,音量比較高,音量比較高
The wave size of its sound is related to its volume, the higher the volume, the more and longer the volume of my wave
它的聲音的波大小跟它的音量,越高,我波的音量越多,越長
Then this is very interesting, this Pip is in seven hundred and thirty-three
那這個就是很有趣的,這個比普在七百三十三十二
This is Staphylococcus aureus
這個是金黃色葡萄球菌
All Glanz Yang Zhijun has this one strong signal
所有格蘭茲楊志俊都有這一個很強的訊號
I've been talking to him for five years
我已經跟他講了五年了
Why must follow his 8 points
為什麼一定要按照他的8分
In fact, there are infinitely many low-pitched
其實有無窮多的音很低
which sound is dishonest
哪一個音是不老實的
good
好
next
接下來
I can't do this look anymore
我不能再做這個動作的樣子
good
好
just use this air
就用這個空氣的樣子
Well, at the end of the speech, thanks to the people who actually did the work
好 演講到最後總之要感謝那些真正做事的人
people who actually do things
真正做事的人
People who are squinting and rolling their eyes are usually right.
這 吞嘰光白眼的人通常都是沒錯
So I'm just thinking about it
所以我這邊就在想想想
It was the three of us who went there together
就是我們三個人一起去達當年的
This phenomenon of speech in life
人生演講的這個現象
The life speech that awards us the Lord
那頒獎給我們當主的人生演講
please stand
請就立
He is Wang Jianchang
他就是王建長
adults are there
還大人在那裡
he is also avoided
他也是人們所避免的
He is the current member director
就是現在的會員局長
so you are in our building
所以你在我們建築中
I saw one in the medical room
在醫療房間都看到一張
That's the one
就是那個
Photo by Li Hong
李宏劈照
he holds the award
他拿著這個獎
that good name that didn't last long
沒有多久的那個好名點
He felt that he had seriously misspoken it.
他就覺得他就把它認真講錯了
His name is Li Hongpi
他都叫李宏劈
He also wants to promise you
他也想答應你
please stand
請就立
It was sold to the general district of Minse City
就賣給了民色市的總區
He is also a material master
他也是一個材料主人
He helped us do half of the related
他幫我們做一半相關
This is my assistant Zhou Beita
這就是我的助理周貝他
sent in the one who risked his life to do it
送進那個冒生危險來做的
that situation
那個情境
of our group
我們的集團局的
The sense of branching in that situation goes
那個情境裡面的分支感去
is a lot of things
是一個很多的東西
That's Dr. Han
那就是韓醫師就是
National Taiwan University
台大那個
Prescription Medicine for Critical Illness
重症方章醫學
Follow the gymnastics from the Corleys
都跟著那個科利家的體育師
That's because everyone knows that
那因為那個大家都知道
Music in Taiwan is in very bad shape right now
台灣的音樂現在狀況非常糟
So there are four major interfaces
所以都是四大接口
important reset
重要的重定的
All doctors are unwilling to come
都醫生都不願意來
A non-surgical
一個無外科啦
So he's got it now
所以他現在已經心得到
He wants to be that Zifan himself
他自己要當那個子凡的
Zifan's Zizi
子凡的子子
Then you have two kids
然後就要帶兩個小孩子
Then you have to talk to Mr.
然後還要跟他先生
Zifan's Zifan wants to be with him
子凡的子凡要跟他一起
there are these
就有這些
I want to read that again
自己又要念那個
very very right to him
對他非常非常對
This is it
就是這個
when this powerless
那這個無力無調的時候
he wears a high heel low
他就帶一個太大的高跟低
just pronounce it
就給他發音
gotta find that
就要找到那個
very big
很大的
great indicator
很大的指標
A very important payment is
一個很重要的支付就是
I just found out that it is Red Soup Technology
我剛剛知道就是紅湯科技
if
如果
If someone is buying refills
有人在買補調的話
Mr.'s complement
那個先生的補調
Just make another one if you can make up for it
幫補調的就再做一個
make some adjustments
弄一些調
Gongzi Park
公子園
In the end, I would like to thank everyone for your advice.
那最後我就謝謝大家的指教
Of course he would like to thank the National Guest Association
他當然要感謝國客會
There are many universities in Zhuangdui
莊一堆還有很多的大學
There are many universities
對裡面有很多的大學
then this is
那這個是
I want to invite everyone
我這一部要請大家
You have seen our host come
大家有看到我們主持人來
so let me mention
所以我給大家提一下
Thank you everyone
感謝大家
platform one by one
站台的一個一個
Because our article was published
因為我們那個文章發表
When the article about drama was published
抓戲劇的那一個文章發表的時候
This enters everyone
這個進入到大家位
then i will stop here
那我就講到這裡
almost time
時間差不多
exactly twenty minutes
有二十分鐘剛好
answer the questions
回答問題
in this way
這樣子
ok thank you all
好謝謝大家
that just had
那個剛剛有
after already having an audience
已經有觀眾之後
That continuous sound is not good
那個續續的聲音不好聽啊
then we start
那我們開始
that Q&A
那個Q&A
good
好
Committee members
委員同學
Um
嗯
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精采的演講
i think that place is
我想那個地方是
I mentioned that there are many kinds of antibiotics
我提到抗生素有很多種
In the experiment, we just talked about Wangu B&B
實驗裡面剛剛講萬古民宿
Your information just now said
你們剛剛的資料是說
it's the outer skin of that cell
它是對那個細胞的外皮
However, there is another data
可是另外也有一個資料是
Seems like a new one for protein synthesis
好像是新的一個針對蛋白質合成的
But protein synthesis is in that
可是蛋白質合成是在那個
Occurs in the center of large cells
大大的細胞中間發生的
like you just said
就像您剛剛講的
If the area of ​​the slide
如果投影片的區域的話
that would be a big one
那會很大一個
those things
那這些事情
when contained in the middle of the cell
包含在細胞中間的時候
your technique doesn't mean
你的技術不是說
Should be close to that win
應該會在那個贏得很靠近的時候
It will be strengthened around that
在那個附近才會增強
then you are so far inside the cell
那你那麼遠在細胞裡面
can't you hear it
是不是就聽不出來
In fact the most likely
事實上最可能的
I'm guessing of course
我當然就是猜測
because i didn't see
因為我沒有看到
that most likely is
那最可能的就是
In fact, it's been a long time
其實話很久
that cell
那細胞
bacteria are alive
細菌是活著
so when its insides start to get attacked
所以當它的內部開始受到攻擊的時候
and it starts emitting all kinds of different molecules
它就會開始散發出各種不同的分子
Then our goodness is actually
那我們良大的其實是
The molecules emitted by the so-called scream
所謂慘叫聲之它散發出來的分子
will eventually run until there is some running
終究會跑到有一些跑步
what sounds do we hear when we come outside
到外面來的時候我們聽到的是哪些聲音
Then please don't ask me which molecule those sounds represent
那請你不要問我說那些聲音代表的是哪一個分子
I've been doing this for so many years, I only dare to tell people
我做了這麼多年我只敢跟人家講說
I wish I could say it again here
我希望我在這邊再講一次好了
I hope
我希望
this
這個
This 732 this Optics Valley
這個732這個光谷
from which molecule
到底是來自哪一個分子
because of all
因為所有的
Both Galanz and Young's bacteria have a very strong optical valley
格蘭士、楊世俊都有非常強的這個光谷
That's not what we saw in the lab
那已經不是我們實驗室看到
This thing has been seen for 10 years
這件事情已經看到10年
I have been telling you for 3 years
那我已經跟大家講了3年
You said I wish my lab was the first to know
你說我希望我的實驗室是第一個知道
Which molecule is that sound coming from?
那一個聲音是來自哪一個分子
That
那
I hope I'm still saying the same thing to you in less than 3 years
我希望我不到3年之後還是跟你講同樣一句話的
Doing basic research is a very hard work
做基礎研究是一個非常辛苦的事情
but that thing
但是那件事情
when you see a regularity
當你看到一個規律性
Why did Grand City and Yang Shijun have this signal
為什麼格蘭市、楊世俊都有這個訊號
The thing is that he has a regularity
這件事情就是他有一個規律性
Like saying why the sun at what time of the year
就像說為什麼太陽在每年的什麼時候
the longest days
日子都會最長
When this thing is observed
那這件事情觀測到的時候
Then when you go to understand the truth
那你去了解那個道理的時候
You may discover the three laws of overcoming
你就有可能發現克服的三大定律
That's what attracts us
那這件事情才是吸引我們的
That is, we are in a very complicated and complicated environment
就是我們在很複雜很複雜的環境當中
We suddenly hear a constant
我們突然聽到一個不變的東西
the constant
那個不變的東西
There must be a reason behind it
它背後一定有一個道理
We have pursued for so many years
我們追求了這麼多年
that's what you're asking
就是在問的是那樣的問題
As for saying
至於說
people want to ask me to talk
人家要問我說話
Is this word going to be useful? It's useless
這個字要有用嗎?沒用
Those things because of nano-country new Spanish
那些事情因為奈米國家新西話
Ask me every day if there is any industrial application
每天都要問我說有沒有什麼產業化應用
i have to say
我只好說
How much is the output value
產值多少
let's talk to him
我們就跟他講說
if so
如果這樣子的話
I'll sell you a drama for 1 yuan
我賣給你一支戲劇的賣1塊錢就好
Then we all sent
那我們大家都發了
Everyone has a few hundred
每個人身上都會有幾百
a gigabit like this
一千兆之這樣子
so this
所以這
this is an interesting question
這個是一個有趣的問題
I think it's the molecules
我覺得就是那些分子
What is the molecule that produces and teaches students?
就是產教生的分子是什麼分子
i really have no way to answer
我真的沒有辦法回答
And that's probably not the best thing to do
而且那也恐怕不是最值得去
because it changes too much
因為它變化太多
when things are too complicated
太複雜的事情的時候
you have no way to answer
你沒有辦法去回答
be a researcher
做一個研究工作者
Maybe you have to measure whether you are old or not
可能要衡量自己年紀是不是已經
I'm about to retire
到了快退休了
Then tell me how old you are
那這時候就說你有多少年生
can answer a certain type of question
可以回答某一類型的問題
All right
好吧
good
好
second question
第二個問題
do you sell that a crazy
你把那個賣一個瘋狂嗎
click it once
按一下
Thanks
謝謝
thank you
謝謝您
I remember one is
我想起一個就是
one of our present human rights
我們現在的一個人權
There is no avoidance of an advancement
也沒有避免的一個進階
or like before playing a game
或者是說像玩遊戲前
I think the life of things
我想東西的生命性
we are doing such a job
我們在做這樣的一個工作
The white snowball is bigger than the red wine
白雪球是比紅酒都還大的
Viruses are much smaller than bacteria
病毒是比細菌小很多
In fact such a spectrum
事實上這樣的光譜
From Viruses From Viruses Such Spectrum
從病毒來自於病毒的這樣的光譜
is already done
是已經有人做了
I didn't do it because I didn't want to
我之所以沒做不是因為我不想做
but because of dealing with viruses
而是因為處理病毒
I talked to him at the original branch
我在原分所跟他講說
when i was studying bacteria
我在研究細菌的時候
All of our directors know how to make brows
我們所長都是會做眉頭的
The lab guy next door said you were crazy
隔壁的實驗室人就講說你瘋了
It's you who are going to poison us to death
就是你準備把我們毒死
you are going to kill us
你要害死我們
So the purpose of my coming today is
所以我今天來的目的就是
speak forcefully
要強力的跟大家講
Professor Xu Mingda's point of view
徐明達教授的觀點
is to give bacteria you supply
就是要給細菌你供到
you have a kilo
你身上有一公斤
I have a kilo
我身上有一公斤
then you tell me
然後你跟我對著我講
I'm all comrades tell me
我都同志跟我講說
you are going to kill me
你要把我害死
Who Killed Who?
到底是誰把誰害死
I do not even know
我都不知道
I'm for this matter
那我為了這件事情
I had to write another one
只好又去寫了一個
The Industrial Plan of Science and Technology Development Fund
科發基金的產業計畫
Then let's study what are xenobiotics
那我們研究什麼叫做異生菌
someone was asking me before
以前有人在問我
I am studying xenobiotics
我中間研究異生菌的
Our laboratory only studies xenobiotics
我們實驗室只研究異生菌
You're wasting your yogurt every day
你每天優格都喝得浪費
Then recently I found a very interesting topic
然後最近我找到一個非常有趣的題目
I just wrote a letter today to a professor at the Central University
今天我才寫一個信給那個中心大學的一個教授
He is a xenobiotic of lactic acid-susceptible bacteria cultured from breast milk
他是從母乳當中培養出來的乳酸感菌的異生菌
this is a very interesting idea
這是有一個非常有趣的想法
Because many children develop allergies
因為很多小孩子就開始過敏
The problem with every system is that they don't drink breast milk
每一系統出問題是他們沒有喝母乳
If we feed him xenobiotics from breast milk
如果我們是從母乳的出來的異生菌來餵他的話
Then this thing may be a very, very likely effective motivator
那這件事情可能是一個非常非常有可能有效的動力
that's interesting
那有趣的是這樣
is the real effect of xenobiotics
就是異生菌的真正的效果
The FDA all over the world has not said that he has an effect
全世界的FDA都沒有說他有效果
That's what the manufacturers say
都只有廠商在說的這樣子
'Cause what they say they say the whole show
因為他們講的都說什麼整場見慰
No one can say he is right or wrong
就沒有人能夠說他錯對不對
After that, there is another kind of xenobiotic bacteria that say yes
那之後什麼還有一種的異生菌說是
After drinking it, you can adjust your figure
喝了又可以身材瞄調
I would also like to study this
我也很想研究這樣
I'm currently working towards that direction
目前我正在往那個方向努力
For fear of being kicked out of National Taiwan University by my colleagues
為了怕被我的同事把我趕出台大
So I'm going to start today by announcing
所以我今天要先宣布
please go out and talk
請大家出去就講說
Professor Wang is studying probiotics
王教授研究的是易生菌
May I ask if the Virus has any sound?
請問那個Virus有沒有聲音
yes yes of course
有有 當然有
As long as it is a molecule, it will have a sound
只要是分子都會有聲音
The voice actually says
聲音其實就是說
atoms themselves do not oscillate
原子本身不會震盪
Then you take two green, green atoms
那你拿兩個青 青原子
become a blue molecule
變成一個青分子
it's right there when it rises
它就在那正起來的時候
you can measure its frequency
你就可以量到它的頻率
that can now
那現在可以
Can this be applied to
這個可以不可以應用到
the flu one
流行性感冒的那個
theoretically possible
理論上都可以
But sample inferiority and collaborators are very important
但是樣品自卑還有合作者是很重要
Then if there is a Virus
那如果有做那個Virus
It's the influenza researcher.
是流行性感冒的那個研究人
their laboratory
他們實驗室
Whether it is a P3 or P4 laboratory
不管是P3還是P4的實驗室
Let's go and help him set up something like this
我們去幫他設一套這樣的東西
As long as he chats with me so that we all have a good time
只要他跟我聊天聊得我們大家相談甚歡的話
I'm willing to send a set of machines over there to study with him
我都願意送一套機器過去那邊跟他一起研究
in this way
這樣子
i am very patient
我是非常有耐心的
For example, when we went to the Jilin Pavilion, we have sent that machine in for three or four years.
像我們到吉林館自己已經送那個機器進去三四年了
We have not published any articles
我們沒有發表任何一篇文章
did not publish any articles
沒有發表任何一篇文章
we just keep doing it
我們就繼續的一直在做
This is a philosophy that I personally do research on
這是我個人做研究的一種哲學
Then I am not worried that Dean Synchronization sent me away
那我那個很不擔心同步院長把我發了掉
right
對
no two small problems
沒有兩個小問題
One is Xijing's stage
一個就是細菁的那個stage
that situation
那個狀況
Reaction of the young and old
年輕老那些的反應
There is another problem
還有另外一個問題就是
What's the reaction of Xijing's mix together?
細菁的mix在一起那個反應怎麼樣
These two things are what I really want to do
這兩個事情都是我很想做的
but i can only tell you now
但是我現在只能告訴您說
that's all mine
那都是我的
Just told my students the other day it was all mine
前兩天才跟我的學生們講說那都是我的
dream thing
夢想中的事情
but it's very interesting
但是是非常有趣的
of course i will
我當然會
I put a careful one over there
我把一隻細心擺在那邊
then he watched him grow up
然後他看他長大
that side grew up
那一邊長大
when he split
他要分裂的時候
He must have different molecules coming out
他一定會有不同的分子出來
At the moment when we are about to divide
那正要分的那一剎那的時候
does he exude
他是不是散發出
when the child was born
那個生小孩的時候
This and that miserable student
這個那個慘教生
maybe everyone knows
可能是大家都知道
Many female compatriots know
很多女性同胞都知道
That was when Mr. was beaten
那或是先生被打的時候
is also miserable
也是慘教
That miserable student
那那個慘教生
can we hear
是不是我們可以聽得到
This is all my Dream Experiment
這都是我的Dream Experiment
But I've been speaking for five years
但是我已經講了五年了
My students get married and ignore me
我的學生大婚都不理我
so
這樣
every time i tell them
我每次跟他們講說
This pair of XI-DEM
這對XI-DEM
then they all said
然後他們都說
yes teacher
是啊 老師
You are all XI-DEM
你都XI-DEM
so
這樣
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝
turn off
關掉
Hello Mr. Wang
王老師您好
I am in the doctor's office of Beijing Medical University
我在北醫的念博士辦
Now pronounce it Cantor
那現在念做Cantor
Cantor's social development
Cantor的社會來的培養
Do Cantor
做Cantor的
Metastases
Metastase
to transfer that research
以轉移的那個研究
Just started
剛開始
Then what I want to ask is a
那我要問的是一個跟
Expert in Pharmaceutical Physics and Chemistry
藥物物理跟化學的專家
The problem with the second temperature is
二溫的問題是
You recently saw the article
你最近看到文章
in cancer cells
在癌症的細胞
this cell it is doing
這個細胞它在做
when it floats in the water
它在漂浮在水中的時候
Then use laser two spectrum to pull it
然後用雷射兩光譜去拉它
How do you know this Optic Tracer
你知道這個Optic Tracer的方式
Nayu that characteristic
那由那種特性
How Q is it?
它的那個有多Q啊
that elasticity
那個彈性
can represent how vicious it is
可以代表它有多兇惡
Then from normal cells
然後從正常細胞
one gets worse
一個變得越來越壞
this becomes diversion
這會變成轉移
cancer cell
癌細胞
Finally it will transfer to that cell
最後它會轉移到那個細胞
Its elasticity is getting more and more Q
它的這個彈性越來越Q
So the question I want to ask is
那我想問的問題就是說
Lamination
Lamination
Cells can be studied in the middle of floating objects
可以在漂浮的物體中間研究細胞
me because of my stuff
我因為我這個東西
to magnify the matter
為了要放大這件事
it can only be pasted
它只能貼上來
So this is the limitation of this technique
所以這是這個技術的限制
then you don't need to do this
那你不需要做這件事
You can consider doing Laman
你可以去考慮做拉滿就好
That's because the cells are really big
那因為其實細胞是很大的
so you know it floats over there
所以你知道它漂浮在那邊
Then you use an Optic Tracer
那你就用一個Optic Tracer
after grabbing it
去把它抓住之後呢
You use laser light on it
你再把它用雷射光
same laser light
同樣那個雷射光
you measure its luster
你就去量它的光澤
You hope to directly get the slow and wide service under the different pulling force of the cell itself
你有希望直接拿到那個細胞本身的不同的拉力以下的拉慢廣服
you can get it
你可以拿得到
I don't know how to explain it after pulling it
那拉到之後到底怎麼解釋我不知道
But this is a very interesting experiment
但是這個是一個非常有趣的實驗
But I also tell my students that it is also my dream experiment.
但是也算是我也會跟我的學生講說那也是我的夢想的實驗
But if you want to do that, you are welcome to come to our lab to do it
但是如果你要做那個歡迎你到我們實驗室去做
good
好
That Wang novel is because a lot of people just talked about the virus
那個王小說因為剛剛很多人講到病毒
Well, we have that insect virus.
那正好我們有那種昆蟲的病毒
Then this is usable and has been approved for safety.
那這個是能用的已經都被安全核准
So a virus that is absolutely harmless to humans
所以對人絕對沒有害的病毒
and it can be saved
而且是可以存化的
Then this is
那這個也就是
You'll go viral in no time
你這樣會病毒到區一下子
real
真的
What about the flu virus just now?
那另外剛剛講到流感病毒的話
The flu virus is indeed that they are very unkempt
流感病毒的確是他們外表很不整齊
I don't know what happens to people's stomachs
我不要清楚人們關乎肚子會怎麼樣
Then I don't have a virus now, but I am infected with a virus, and I look neat
那我現在沒有病毒是感染病毒外表很整齊
So I guess it might be better to read the light map
所以我猜想讀起來可能光圖會比較漂亮一點
Then it involves the pick you just mentioned
那這裡面涉及到你剛剛講說那個pick
What molecule does it represent?
到底是代表什麼分子
Maybe it's infected with a virus
說不定這個感染病毒
I said that insects can help with a similar answer
我說昆蟲的可以幫忙做一點類似的解答
That means we can take that
那也就是說我們可以把那個
Influenza's surface protein called Hemagotinin
流感的表面蛋白質叫Hemagotinin
It is the obvious element that is the most important antigen
就是明顯素那是最主要的那個 antigen
can be transplanted onto virus-infected surfaces
可以把它移植到感染病毒的表面上來
So in this case
所以這樣情況之下
You can read that molecule's pick
你可以讀到那個分子的pick
I'm guessing because I'm leading the way and don't understand at all
我猜想啦,因為我在領著完全不懂
but i mean, the flu
但是我意思說,流感的
a lot of protein on it
它上面很多蛋白質
You can't quite figure out exactly what protein you're reading about
你會搞不太清楚到底你讀到什麼一個蛋白質
But if you move its protein to the time when the virus is infected for 3 minutes
但是你如果把它蛋白質移到那個感染病毒3分的時候
You will see, because the infection virus must have its original spectrum
你會看到,因為感染病毒一定有它原來的光譜嘛
Then you have one more protein, the protein is quite big
那你多一個蛋白質那蛋白質蠻大的
you will see a special pick
你會看到一個特別pick
I'll start off by saying that we maybe the two of us should sit down
我先講,就是我們也許我們兩個應該坐下來
like the failure to say that two people chatted
就像失敗的說兩個人聊的那樣
yes , yes , are dating your colleagues
是,是,是,都在約你們的同事
Today's A election is not suitable for talking about such reality
今天這場A選不適合談那麼實
short story just one sentence
話短說只有一句話
that is, not every molecule of every
就是並不是每一個分子的每一個
I just showed you the vibration
我剛剛給大家看振動
you can hear every sound
每一個聲音你都聽得到
because it has the problem of choosing symmetry
因為它有選擇的對稱性的問題
So there are some vibrating mannequins
所以有一些振動的模特兒
it is impossible to vibrate out
它是沒有辦法振出來
so you're pretty sure
所以你就很確定說
I put this protein on
我把這一個蛋白質放上去
doesn't mean you can hear it
並不表示它的聲音你聽得到
this is called
這個是有所謂的
in quantum mechanics
量子力學裡面的
selection problem
selection的問題
So this is what we're going to talk about in more detail
所以這個是我們要談更細的
When it comes to this level
要談到這個層次的時候
I think we are more suitable to do in
我想我們就比較適合做在
the two of us wait a minute and we'll go get coffee
我們兩個等一下我們就去喝咖啡
Then make a model
然後做模子吧
mold
模子
OK
好不好
It's more appropriate for us to talk in private.
我們再私底下談比較恰當
good
好
Teacher, your speech is really touching
老師您的演講真的非常令人感動
Then the question I want to extend is to say
那我想要延伸的請教就是說
Because the current platform is
因為現在的平台是
is on the fix the plate
是在fix the plate上面
Is it possible for us
那我們有沒有可能
convert it to a format
把它轉換一個format
For example, it looks like a pig
譬如說類似像在慈豬的樣子
Is it possible for him to become like a missile?
那他有沒有可能性變成像導彈一樣
Go to our Target with something like this
帶著這樣的東西去找我們的Target
For example, cancers that are hard to find and detect
譬如說像很難找其偵測的癌症
Hard-to-find things like lung cancer or soft-slot cancer
像肺癌或者是軟槽癌這種很難找到的東西
Someone is doing such a laboratory
這樣的實驗室有人在做
but that means
但是這就是說
is that theoretically you make some molecules on top of the surface
就是理論上你在表面上面做一些分子
Those molecules are theoretically conceivable
那些分子理論上這都是可以想像的
Then he likes cancer and doesn't like cancer
那他就喜歡癌症不喜歡癌症
These are our own wishes
這些都是我們自己希望的
Then go down and find
那接著就下去找
At this time, let's go back to the issue of the white grass hidden in the Shenlong room that I just talked about.
那這時候就回到我剛剛講的神龍室藏白草的問題
Then maybe you should talk to Dean Wang Qihui about this issue
那就也許應該去找汪奇惠院長談這樣的問題
Then if the molecule you found has been found
那如果你找到的那一個分子已經找到
Then I said I'm wrapping it on a magnetic bead now
那我說我現在把它包在一個磁珠上面
Then I use magnetic beads to pull it out with a magnetic field
然後接著我就磁珠再把它用磁場把它拉出來
This kind of thing has been done for ten or twenty years.
這樣的事情已經有人做了十幾二十年了
Then this has nothing to do with the spectrum we just talked about today.
那這個跟我們剛剛今天講的那個光譜是沒有關係的
Is there anyone doing that kind of experiment?
那那樣的實驗有沒有人正在做
doing now
現在在做
In fact, someone is looking for
事實上是有人專門在找
Secure the In-Tool Mo'Share
Secure the In-Tool Mo'Share
For example, our base center
比方說我們基底中心
Professor Zhang Yingzhi in the Foundation Center
基底中心裡面的張英智教授
you can go talk to everyone
你就可以去跟大家談
He has a special problem in doing this
他就有專門在做這一方面的問題
If so
那這樣子的話
Do you want to do experiments like that
你想要做那個那樣的實驗
i don't understand at all
我是完全不懂的
You go to talk to Zhang Yingzhi and the others
你去找張英智他們談
There may be a better way to answer more accurately
可能會比較有辦法回答更精準
That's because I'm using the way I'm familiar with
那因為我用的是我熟悉的方式
that their way
那他們的那種方法
I'm more obsessive
我都是比較倒聽突說的
So you should still talk to an expert
所以你還是應該跟專家談比較好
OK
好不好
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
he first and then you
他先然後再你
Professor Wang please
王教授請問一下
The area just mentioned refers to the two atomic groups
剛剛講到的那個區域是指兩個原子團
be close enough
要靠得夠近的
Or must two nanometer atoms be close enough
還是說一定要兩個奈米的原子靠得夠近
no no
不是不是
Nano particles are not atoms
奈米的粒子不是原子
inside a nanoparticle
一個奈米粒子裡面
Like the one at 25, there is still
像25的那個奈裡面還有
There are 1 million atoms in a particle of 25 nanometers
25奈米的粒子裡面還有100萬顆原子
25 nanometers and 1 million atoms
25奈米還有100萬顆原子
So atoms are much smaller than that
所以原子是比那個小更多的
Atoms are very, very small
原子是非常非常小的
i can tell you
我可以跟大家講的
Our surface nails are so big
我們的表面指甲大這麼大
I dial a layer of atoms down
我撥一層的原子下來
just dial it down
就把它撥一層下來
every atom
每一顆原子
If anyone wants to buy one from me
如果有人願意一顆跟我買
a dollar
一塊錢的話
that total cost
那那個總經費
Yes, our national budget can last for a thousand years
是可以我們國家預算一千年
But I sell you atoms for a year
可是我賣一年給你原子
Our Institute of Atomic and Molecular Research has started selling atoms
我們原子分子研究所開始在賣原子
Just peel off the top of my nails
只有把我指甲上面撥一層下來
Just drop so much every day
就是每天都要掉那麼多
so what are you asking
所以你問的呢
what about this hot zone
那這個熱區是怎麼樣
The hot zone is these two
熱區就是這兩顆
Two lumps of a million atoms
兩坨一百萬個原子的
This is durable
這個耐以立之
very very close
靠得非常非常近
by the distance between them
靠到它們之間的距離
about twenty atoms
大概是在二十個原子
when i only have that distance
我只有那樣的距離的時候
The laser light in the middle comes in and says
中間那個雷射光照進來說
form a strong consensus
形成一個共識很強
Inside those million atoms
那一百萬個原子裡面
and more than a million electrons
還有也是一百萬還多的電子
That electron flies to the electricity
那一電子飛到電上
when you stand up
站起來的時候呢
they seem to be out of alignment
它們就好像不齊
like a
就像一個
one is twice
一個是兩次
right next to your ear
就在你耳朵邊這樣
then
然後就
That's very powerful, that is to say, the molecule in the middle emits a very intense light.
那這很厲害說中間的那個分子就發出很劇烈的那個光線出來
That's what this whole story is about
那這個就是這整個故事在講的就是這件事情
It was an unexpected discovery that only two
那以前意外的發現就是只有能做兩個
Then our contribution is that when we turn stupid beans into ice at once, it is the rule of hundreds of millions of rows
那我們的貢獻是我們一下子傻豆成冰就是幾億顆排的規矩
make it fast
就很快的規矩把它做出來
Then it is like a net to be on top of it
然後這樣的話就好像一個網一樣要在它上面
That is a bacterium with a thousand of these nanometers underneath
那個是一支細菌的底下還有一千顆這樣的奈米之間
Therefore, the whole signal is relatively high from the revival and the stability is also good.
所以整個訊號就相對的是可從復興高然後穩定性也是好的
are relative
都是相對的
So the nanometer refers to its distance not its length
所以說那個奈米是指它的距離不是它的長度
Then you refer to each distance
那你指的各個的距離
is the distance between the two of them is the interval
就是它們兩個之間的距離就是間隔
Between strong disadvantages and strong disadvantages
強弊跟強弊之間
Their average distance is thirty nanometers
它們的平均距離是三十奈米
there is one in the middle
那中間有一個
A gap with nanometers is a gap
有奈米的Gap 就是一個空隙
That gap is still the worst place for the confrontation
那那個空隙裡面還是那個對陣的最慘的地方
Sound is from vibrations between two atoms
聲音是來自兩個原子之間的振動
that's how to strengthen it
那是怎麼樣把它加強
It's the function of the flat nanosphere
是那個奈米平球的功能
Wang Zhongsheng, do you have
王中生你有沒有
Then you are very reluctant to say
那你都很勉強是說
Hope is by means of visual molecules
希望是藉由視覺上的分子
on a metal surface
放在金屬表面
Then the specific light comes down
然後特定光照下來
reflected by it
藉由它反射出來
Specific inside light map
特定裡面的光圖
Then look at the general idea of ​​its molecules
然後來看看它的分子的總念
in that and that chemistry
那這個那個化學中
The Khing Lim Finger that mentions Bohr
那個提到波爾的慶林指淋節
mention the first layer
就提到第一顆層
and then absorb specific ingredients
然後吸收特定的原料
Then Yaoqing went back to the basic one
然後藥清回到基礎那個
Tell me which grade you are in first
你先跟我講你是哪一個年級的學生
I am a sophomore in Yanfeng Middle School
我是嚴峰中學高二學生
Then you are very, very good
那你程度非常非常好
you just said
你剛才說
You're talking about ball picking chemistry
你這講是選球化學
OK good
OK 好
very good
非常好
that one thing is different
那一件事情是不一樣的
That is also the energy level of the main circle of electrons
那也是電子要圈的能階
Now we're talking about a party between two atoms
現在講的是兩個原子之間的政黨
Electronic circle is
電子要圈是
Electrons are much lighter than atoms
電子比原子還輕很多
should know
應該知道
e.g. for example
電子比方說舉個例子
is the weight of light atoms
就是輕原子的重量
It is the difference between the weight of a direct son and an electron
就是直子的重量跟電子的差別
It's two thousand times worse
是差兩千倍
People often don't understand
大家常常是沒了解說
The difference between that electron and ours is that
那個電子跟我們的差別就是說
if you are if you are electronic
你如果是假如你是電子的話
That light atom is the lesson of the M60
那輕原子就是M60的堂課
so electrons are small
所以電子是很小的
will wrap around
會繞在外面
Is there just one electron?
就一個電子有沒有
Then this electron has various orbital domains
那這個電子有各種不同的軌域
when it starts beating
它開始跳動的時候
it also glows
它也會發光
Then this is the other one called
那這個是另外那個叫做
A spectrum emitted by electrons
電子發出來的一個光譜
That's an electronic spectrum
那也是一種電子譜
That's not what we're talking about now
那我們現在講的不是那件事情
Talking about a handful of two
講的是一把兩顆
When the golden circles are placed together
金圓子擺在一起的時候
One of their mother's relatives
他們母親的一個親分字吧
The middle character of these two parent characters
這些兩個親分字的中間字
can be proved like this
可以這樣證明到
like dumbbells
就跟啞鈴一樣
can go over there
可以在那邊走
It turns out that it can be proved like this
原來證起來它就可以這樣
Then this has a legitimate frequency
那這個有一個正當頻率
this legitimate frequency
這個正當頻率
That's what I just said
就是我剛剛講大概
The sound we just played to you
我們剛剛播給你聽的聲音
multiply by 3 by 10 the house of the cross
乘以3乘以10的十字房
I just lied to you on purpose
我剛剛是故意騙你們
Just take that 3 times 10 cross room
就把那個3乘以10的十字房
just remove it
就把它除掉了
So deliberately pretend that there is no such number
所以故意裝作說沒那個數字
then you hear
然後你就聽到了
It's actually that simple
其實就這麼簡單而已
OK, here's the one that plays
OK,這是一個播放的那個
It's all a lie to you
其實都是騙你們的
Professor Na Huang
那黃教授
you just mentioned
你剛剛提到說
no way to know now
現在沒有辦法知道說
That frequency is specially bought a molecule
那個頻率是特地買個分子
is there a way to do this
那有沒有辦法做到這件事情
There is a way
有辦法
It's theoretically possible
就是理論上都是有辦法
but that's called need
但是那叫需要
very very hardworking graduate student
非常非常用功的研究生
Well, we don't have people like that
那我們先是沒有那樣的人這樣
Thanks
謝謝
ok one last question
好,最後一個問題
Hello, Mr. Wang, I would like to ask
王老師你好 我想請問一下
Because of your research, I remember that there was a press conference last year or the year before
因為您的研究我記得在去年還是前年有記者會
At that time, it was said that this method could quickly screen the pathogenic bacteria of septicemia
那時候是說用這個方法可以快速篩選那個敗血病的病物菌
Then I want to ask if so far
那我是想問那到目前為止有沒有
For example, it was reported by National Taiwan University Hospital
比如說像那時候是台大醫院報告的
Has that big hospital used this method in clinical practice?
那台大醫院有沒有用這個方式用在臨床上面了
i and they already hinted to you
我跟他們已經跟你暗示
That is when you start to really face the reproductive world
就是說當你開始真的面對生殖的世界的時候
the pain just started
那個痛苦才開始來
When you write a thesis, all your imagination is very pure
你在寫論文的時候就是一切想像都是很單純的
But when you get a drop of blood
可是當你拿到一滴血的時候
My first thing is that it's still blood from a healthy person.
我第一件事情就是那還是健康人的血
The nurse lady mentioned it to me first
那個護士小姐就先跟我提到說
Teacher, there are many patients' blood in the blood of real patients
老師啊 真正病人的血裡面有很多病人的血
Half a barrel is filled with oil floating on top
半桶是油在裡面浮在上面的
Because he eats very well
因為他那個吃得非常好
So eat half of it, maybe the oil will be lower
所以吃一半 那個油可能會不會低一下
just listen to all the voices
就先把所有的聲音都聽完
to the sound of oil
到油的聲音
then we have to go on
那我們要做下去
So it's all the same
所以其實這都是一樣
like there is actually another
就像其實有另外一個
A very frequently asked question is to say
很常常問的問題都是說
Then, for example, in mainland China
然後比方說中國大陸的
Everyone three together in peace
大家都三聚清安
Is there Sanjuqing'an in the milk?
牛奶裡面有沒有三聚清安
Of course, this method can also
這個方法當然也可以測
It must be all right
一定這樣都可以
There are also people doing such research
也有人做這樣的研究
The first thing you need to do is put the milk
第一件事情就是你要先把牛奶的
Other impurities in the milk powder must be disposed of first
奶粉其他的雜質先要處理掉
That's all very deep chemistry
那這都是很高深的化學問題
Maybe our vice president can answer
也許我們副院長才有辦法回答
I'm just starting to regret it
我現在才開始就非常後悔
When my blog researcher was interviewed by a reporter
我的博社研究員在被記者訪問的時候
some of the questions he answered
他所回答的一些問題
Because people have a very strange
因為人有個非常奇怪的
That's when the reporters start asking you
就是記者開始問你的時候
The more he talks, the happier he is.
他就越講越高興這樣子
Then Wen Tang said
然後文堂說
You decide how long it will take to finish
你決定大概要多久才能夠弄完
I said it should be over in 30 minutes
我就說應該30分鐘完
Because we have a close relationship
因為我們涼一個關股
It'll cool down in about 5 minutes.
只要大概5分鐘就涼完了
But I don't think so
但是我心裡就想不會吧
that sample pretreatment
那樣品前處理
It might take half a day to deal with that or something.
可能要處理半天那什麼之類的
you really want something that works for the patient
你真的要對病人有用的東西
It takes a lot of practice
是要千錘百練的
So my answer to your question should be clear enough
所以我回答你的問題應該夠清楚
That is to say, we went in very hard.
就是說我們進去很努力的
Never move the machine in
毫不會把機器搬進去
Then I have been doing experiments for others
然後一直在幫人家做實驗
Every day is very depressing
每天都在做很苦悶的
Been doing something I don't understand at all
一直在做一些我完全不懂的事情一樣
just how to put
就是要怎麼把
front of blood
血的前面一些
something that has nothing to do with this matter
跟這個事情沒有關的東西
Then I can use a
那我可以用一個
Talk about the first sentence of Ke Wenzhe's meeting with me in one minute
一分鐘講柯文哲跟我見面的講的第一句
I asked him
我問他說
Dr. Ke
柯醫師
this
這個
Halfblood is really sick, you can see he's dying
半血真的病了你看他已經快死了
Then there are probably a few bacteria in the blood he sucked.
那他一吸一吸的血裡面大概有幾支細菌
because i'm going to catch
因為我要去抓
then you always give me one
那你總要給我一個
Just say that I want to go to a mountain as big as a mountain
就說我要到山上一個這麼大一棵山
to catch the mountain machine
要抓上山機
Then you always tell me how many machines there are in that mountain
那你總要跟我講那山裡面有多少機器
I wouldn't miss it
我也不會沒抓過的
Ke Wenzhe is very like that
柯文哲就非常那種
like he was repeatedly told on tv
就像他電視被反覆的
Professor Huang
黃教授
we should be in this world
我們應該在這個世界上
no one can answer
沒有人辦法回答
This big question should be taken to the people
這大問題應該拿到給人家
Then of course I don't believe it
那我當然就很不相信
Then I really want to say yes when we
那又真的想說好當我們
so i just say
所以我就說
I go abroad everywhere
我到處去到出國
Those outside China may want to cooperate with us
把我國外的可能想要跟我們合作
very big visit
非常大的要訪
everyone is about home
大家有關家
what you're really doing
你真正在做的這樣
he also told me
他也跟我講過
1CC inside
1CC裡面
probably at most 1 to 5
大概頂多1到5
only tinnitus
只能耳鳴
doesn't seem genuine
看起來不成真心
In that 1CC of blood
那1CC的血裡面
What does 1 to 5 mean
1到5是什麼意思
let me tell you again
我再跟大家講一下
1cc of blood
1CC的血
Then you replace it with
那你就把它換成
primary bacteria
一次細菌
That 1CC of blood
那1CC的血
How big is 1CC?
就是變多大的1CC呢
Because our fund is 1 million times
因為我們的基金是100萬倍
That 1CC
那1CC
1CC is 3CC in 1 cm
1CC就是1公分的3CC
then you convert it
那你把它換算起來
How big is that soup
那一湯水大概多大
I convert it
我把它換算起來
For Taipei City
就台北市
You put it as high as Seven Star Mountain
你把它到七星山那麼高
fill it all with water
全部灌滿水
Taipei may be completely flooded with water
台北可能地全部灌滿水
there is a
裡面有一個
Ke Wenzhe is swimming there
柯文哲在那邊游泳
then you say
然後你就說
that's some things to do
那就是要做的一些事情
The difficulty is of course very difficult.
那這個難度當然就非常難了
So biologists don't do such stupid things
那所以生物學家並不做這麼傻的事
Biologists say let's bring it
生物學家就說那就把它來嘛
Then every half hour it changes to two
那每半個鐘頭它就變兩隻
Then do it for another half an hour and it turns into four
然後再做半個鐘頭它就變四隻
Then just wait for three days, right?
然後就等三天嘛對不對
and then on the second
然後就二的
Twenty and forty parties are coming
二十四十方就來了
catch one
一下就抓到一隻
Then they are all the same ethnic group
然後他們都是同一個族群
then you go and listen to him
那你就去聽他就
Why are you grabbing one, right?
你幹嘛要抓一隻嘛對不對
Then it starts to become something
那這時候就開始變成一些
very strange question like this
非常奇怪的問題這樣子
If you catch it, you won't get it, and you won't talk about it.
那抓到也不會拿到都不會來講
but it's not true
可是不是真的話
So I'm looking for him to catch that one
所以就在找他去抓那一隻
Not because I envy you too much
不是因為我太羨慕你
But because of that one thing
可是因為那一件事情
to catch him
要去抓他這件事
There are many physical and chemical grids that are very far away
有很多的物理跟化格是非常遠的
Its a very high question in this challenge circle
它在這個挑戰界非常高的問題
your first reaction is to say
你讓第一個反應就是說
Then I will take all the water in Taipei City
那我就把所有台北市的水
Is it all leaking?
全部漏光嘛
Then I'm the one in the water
那我就在水的那個
Just dig a hole in the city hall
市政府的真中就挖一個洞
The others with that bacterial blue column
那有那個細菌藍柱的其他都
Everything can be done in Ximika
都可以就在細蜜卡在那裡
All the other honeys are gone
其他的小蜜子都掉了
And then take it off when it's big
然後大了就把它撈掉了
it's easy to say
就講得很容易
real things to do
真正可以做的事
Most of the holes are plugged in
大部分的洞都塞進了
then there too
然後也在那裡
So then you can't pretend
所以那你就開始裝不到了
but encouragement from there every day
但每天都從那裡鼓勵
then just say
然後就說
Many questions are asked every day
每天很多問題都話
what's on your mind
你心中的事用
So the real world
所以說真實的世界
Actually something that works
其實真正能用的東西
it costs a lot of money
是要花很多的錢
These things are far from basic research
這些事情跟基礎研究是有段距離
So once there is a breakthrough in basic research
所以基礎研究一旦有突破的時候
It can definitely help a lot of things
它一定就可以幫助很多的事情
So I'm going to talk about it here
所以我在這邊也是要再講
That is to say, Chinese College
就是說中華學院
Chinese studies are in great need of everyone's support
中華研究是非常需要大家支持的
Chinese studies also need to be resolved
中華研究也是需要來來解決的
good
好
I'm usually very good at timing
我通常都是控制時間很準的
because it was supposed to be 11 o'clock
因為本來要11點
end at 9 o'clock
9點完畢
He has two minutes of timeout on his
他有超時的兩分鐘他的
good
好
Our congratulations thank you Huang Yan
我們恭喜謝謝黃岩